<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A method, or briefe instruction; verie profitable and speedy, for the reading and vnderstanding of the old and new Testament The one expounding the other according to the sence and meaning of our our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ.</title>
            <author>Vaughan, Edward, preacher at St. Mary Woolnoth.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14281</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24597</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103028</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838787</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838787</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3176</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14281)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3176)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1158:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A method, or briefe instruction; verie profitable and speedy, for the reading and vnderstanding of the old and new Testament The one expounding the other according to the sence and meaning of our our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ.</title>
                  <author>Vaughan, Edward, preacher at St. Mary Woolnoth.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 115, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by T. Orwin. for W. Holme,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Edward Vaughan.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Study and teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3176:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3176:1"/>
            <p>A Method, or briefe inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; verie profitable and <hi>ſpeedy, for the reading and</hi> vnderſtanding of the old and new Teſtament. (<g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>) The one expounding the other according to the ſence and meaning of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Veritas.</q>
            <q>Bleſſed is that man whoſe delight is in the law of the Lord, and in his law doth exerciſe himſelfe both day and night. <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 1.2.</bibl>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>He ſhall be like a tree planted,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>His leafe ſhall not weither,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>3. Whatſoeuer he dooth ſhall proſper.</item>
               </list>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON. Imprinted by <hi>T. Orwin.</hi> for <hi>W.</hi> Holme. 1590.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <p>Vitam orna docendo: Vaum hoc geſtit Doctrinam Orna Giuendo: Ne ignorata damnetur:</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3176:2"/>
               <p>Teipſum Conſule. Memento Mori. Iuſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>andum ſerua. Praemonitus Praemunitus.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Ieſu eſto mihi Ieſus.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:3176:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <head>To <hi>Theophilus</hi> the vnfeyned louer of Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Act.</hi> 1, 1. and To <hi>Lydia</hi> his wife, the painefull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructer of her houſhold. <hi>Act.</hi> 16.15.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE euill of <hi>ignorance,</hi> how great a ſinne it is not rightlie to knowe God, the common courſe of all Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures in their order, duo partlie teach, that by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour we may in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge excell them, ſeeing by nature they excell vs. And for experience, if the ſoules and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of ignorant men were ſet open but one houre to the world, it would be a world and a warning for euer, to ſee their deſolation, their feare, their ſorrowe and reſolute condemning of themſelues to that place of perdition of bodie and ſoule prepared for the diuell and for them: not knowing which way to winde out, beeing brought in by <hi>Ariadnes</hi> thread, or rather by a corruptible ſeed, that although the light ſhineth in the darkenes of their hearts, yet they cannot comprehend it: becauſe they eyther dispiſe or neglect the knowledge of their <hi>Creator,</hi> which
<pb facs="tcp:3176:3"/> is not to be known to any, but by the knowledge of the holie Scriptures. <hi>What Father or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would not ſigh, and ſowne for hartie ſorrowe to ſee their Children preparing themſelues to hell: what Maſter ſo vnmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull that would not pittie to ſee their ſeruants hearts bleeding for ſorrow?</hi> And what <hi>Paſtor</hi> would not willinglie reſigne all to redeeme one of his charge, although all the reſt were ſaued? Beholde then how carefull ought <hi>Parents</hi> to bee in teaching their Children the instruction of the Lord? and how watchfull e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie <hi>Paſtor</hi> to giue them their meate in due ſeaſon. The Diuell hath receiued many into his Kingdome by ignorance of the Scriptures, and hee ſeeth it is the way to enlarge it: therefore he laboreth bodilie &amp; Ghoſtly, night and day, by craft and by crueltie, to holde men in that miſerable thrall of darkenes, how neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie the knowledge of holy Scriptures is for all people to comfort themſelues, and to confirme o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther many places doo teſtifie. Leu. 19, 17. Deu. 3.12.13.2. Kings 23, 2, 3. Neh. 8, 2. Pſal. 1, 1.2.3. Prou. 1, 1.2, &amp;c. 19, 2.29, 18. 1. Cor. 14, 20. Gal. 6, 1. 1. Theſs. 5.14. 1. Tim. 2, 4. 2. Tim. 2, 24.25.26. Heb. 3.13. Iam. 5, 19.20. 1. Pet. 3, 15.16. Beware of falſe Prophets Math. 7, 15. Trie all things and keepe that which is good.
<pb facs="tcp:3176:3"/> 1. Theſſ. 5, 21. But how can theſe things be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed without the knowledge of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? How ſhall a ſeruant doo the will of his Master, when he knoweth it not? How ſhall a ſonne rightlie obey his Father, wherein he is not taught? And how much leſſe ſhall the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the ſeruant, the Father or the Sonne be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable to the Lord, and Father of all things, or by obedience pleaſe him when his will is not knowne by his word; who in deede is to be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and obeyed according to the line and leuell thereof, and not according to mans fleſhlie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention or worldlie reaſon.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <label>Obiection.</label> 
                  <hi>Yet for all this many obiect and lay for themſelues that the ſtudie of Gods word dooth onelie appertaine to Diuines and men that are not buſied with the affaires and cares of this world.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Alas they are altogeather deceaued by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than who worketh in them that bee ill, alwaies to doubt their ill by preferring ignorance before knowledge: carnall things before ſpirituall, and earthlie before Heauenlie. But Parents must needes haue the knowledge of Scriptures to teach their Children. Gen. 18, 18.19. Exod. 12,
<pb facs="tcp:3176:4"/> 26.27.13, 8.9 10. Deu. 4, 9.10. Pſal. 78, 5. &amp;c. And it is alſo the duetie of euerie houſeholder to instruct their families Gen. 18, 18.19. Act. 10, 2.16, 14.15. Romans. 15, 5. Colloſs. 4.15. Phil. 2.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <label>Obiect.</label> 
                  <hi>Some doo holde themſelues well excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as touching this account, by hard tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile and paines taking in their vocation and calling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Obiect.</label> 
                  <hi>Some by catechiſing in little Bookes, ſome by their worſhipfull and honorable offices in the common weale, and ſome by frequenting Sermons earlie and late.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Obiect.</label> 
                  <hi>Some doo thinke themſelues well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, and their time well ſpent in exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining &amp; ſearching other mens Bookes for faults and errours, thereby to get praiſe and profit: if they finde none, then they hew and ſtrike fiercely at their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and conuerſations, alwaies bearing armour defenſiue to defend their owne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill; and armes offenſiue to aſſaile the
<pb facs="tcp:3176:4"/> good manners of others, whiles they ſhould bee occupied in ſearching their owne errors and faults by the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Obiection.</label> 
                  <hi>Some doo ſpend the remainder of their liues in</hi> Enuie <hi>and</hi> Arrogancie <hi>enterpriſing impreſsion againſt</hi> impreſſion, <hi>Bookes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> Bookes, <hi>Sermon againſt</hi> Sermon.</p>
            </q>
            <p>And thus they bring ſome to neglect the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of the ſacred Bible: ſome to doubt of the trueth and dignitie thereof, and ſome to hate or to despiſe the profeſſors of the ſame. If theſe <hi>Calummators</hi> and buſie bodies were as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to put in practiſe their preaching, as they be to followe after a fault in their liuing, there ſhould be no ſuch neede of <hi>Priſons</hi> for Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors, of <hi>Bridewells</hi> for Libellors, nor of <hi>Hatchets</hi> for traitors.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <label>Obiect.</label> 
                  <hi>Another ſort there is (in their kinde worſe then all theſe) who by their lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning doe diſſwade the vnlearned from that ſtudy and order of reading the Bible which is preſcribed priuatlie and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquelie
<pb facs="tcp:3176:5"/> by a man whoſe life is vnrebuke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, whoſe learning counteruaileth the beſt learned: whoſe good will to all men hath been publiſhed in his Preaching freelie, whoſe vndeſerued and vnanſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable paynes hath beene ſet foorth by Printing, and whoſe godlie zeale and care doth plainelie appeare in thoſe whom he hath taught in the knowledge of Gods moſt holie word, who are in deed as teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of his truth &amp; infallible argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to proue the experience of his</hi> Method <hi>&amp; order of teaching, (which many ignorant men doo controule ſecretly) to be princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall. And what ſhould I ſay more, I doubt not of mildeneſſe of conſtancie, and of the vertue of Gods holy ſpirit in him, ſo as he may liue bouldlie euen at the faces of his aduerſaries, ſtill proſpering in Gods buſines, and verie well in his owne: In the meane time he is honored among them that bee honored, that fortune abateth without fault; and hee is aſhamed among them that bee aſhamed, that fortune en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haunceth without merit; honorable ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour reſteth not in the dignitie that men haue, but in the good workes whereby they deſerue.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:3176:5"/>
            <p>Herein J commend not the beſt, the worſt are not tollerable. There is no more compariſon betwixt the <hi>Arke</hi> and the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> than is betweene <hi>Gods word &amp; worldly welth:</hi> the getting, the keeping and the ſpending of the one is ſin, and the ſeeking of the other is not fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: without the diligent reading of the old &amp; new Teſtament. <hi>Rethorick</hi> is good, I graunt you, to perſwade: <hi>Aſtronomie</hi> is ſit to know the courſe of the Starres. <hi>Geometrie</hi> is profitable to meaſure the Land. <hi>Muſick</hi> is neceſſarie to recreate: <hi>Philoſophie</hi> to take away the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of death. Theſe and the reſt, be they neuer ſo good, ſo fit, ſo profitable, and ſo neceſſarie: yet they are all but as dimme Starres, in reſpect of Diuinitie. The <hi>Phrigian</hi> Harmonie mooued to the Calendes, maketh a great noyſe: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mooued to <hi>Apollo,</hi> is ſtill calme and quiet. <hi>Hiarchion</hi> hearing <hi>Ruphinus</hi> blowe on his Pipe, would neuer after play on his flute, the <hi>Thruſh</hi> although hauing manie good notes, will not ſing in the companie of the <hi>Nightingall.</hi> Euen ſo, let all the world hold their peace, ſit downe and heare Diuinitie. It is like the <hi>Piller of fire</hi> by night, and a <hi>cloudie piller</hi> by day: to conduct the children of <hi>Abraham</hi> through the waſt wilderneſſe of this world, to that ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and euerlaſting kingdome of <hi>Canaan:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3176:6"/> from this miſerable <hi>Meſapotamia,</hi> and out of the bondage of ſinfull fleſh, to a <hi>Gall</hi> anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the eies of the faithfull, that they may ſee and auoide that foule ſpirite <hi>Aſmodeus.</hi> To a Starre, leading all wiſe men to the true worſhip of Ieſus Chriſt: and it is a law to controle vs, a ſheelde to defend vs, and a light to teach vs.</p>
            <p>Seing then it hath ſo manie good vſes, how can we be without the knowledge thereof.</p>
            <p>Seing our iourney &amp; voyage is ſo dangerous, and we ſuch vnſkilfull trauailers: how ſhall we miſſe ſo good a guid?</p>
            <p>Seing wee are all ouerwhelmed with a cloud of darkeneſſe and ignorance: how can we want ſuch a ſkilfull Schoolemaſter?</p>
            <p>And ſeeing we haue all ſorts of enemies hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering vs, &amp; we our ſelues ſo vnfurniſhed, how ſhall wee bee able to ſtand, not hauing on the whole armor of God? How ſhall we quench the fierie darts of the diuell? and what ſhall I ſay more? O that my mouth could cauſe my words to mount ouer all the world, for to make ſuch a deepe impreſſion in the hearts of all men; that neither things abſent, preſent or to come in the loſſe of libertie, liuing, or life ſhould make them to ſtart one iot from the Chriſtian delight, the holie and Heauenlie exerciſe of Gods word.</p>
            <p>Many, no doubt, would more willinglie giue
<pb facs="tcp:3176:6"/> themſelues to this godlie labor, ſeemed not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ble ſo great and tedious.</p>
            <p>And manie might ſoone bee brought to the knowledge thereof, if their Miniſter had either will or abilitie to deuide vnto them the word of God aright.</p>
            <p>For the diſcharge of mine owne conſcience and dutie, in ſome reſpect, hauing no oportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or occaſion otherwiſe offered mee to benefite my brethren: J will deliuer in this booke a ſhort method, and eaſie rule, and a plaine paſſage throughout the Bible to great vſe and profite.</p>
            <p>At the firſt veiw and ſight iudge not raſhlie, let chriſtian modeſty and the bands of loue hold you, vntill ſome time paſſe for proofe of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite.</p>
            <p>And if in anie thing you miſlke it, I humbly praie you mend it: I ſeeke not mine owne praiſe or profite, but in plaine and ſimple ſort, to teach Chriſt Jeſus: in whoſe name J begin and make an end.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your contrieman and ſeruant for Chriſt his ſake, EDVVARD VAVGHAN, Preacher of Gods holie word in London at S. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Wolnor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="table">
            <pb facs="tcp:3176:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3176:7"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct your ſelfe throughout the Bible, by learning how manie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ookes are in euerie part: and howe manie Chapters euerie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ooke containeth: The profit I cannot brieflie vtter, if you acquaint your ſelfe in the ſame with this order.</p>
            <list>
               <head>The whole Bible may be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered foure fould.</head>
               <item>Legall.</item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Exod.</hi> 40.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Leui.</hi> 27.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Num.</hi> 38</item>
                           <item>1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 31.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>New</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Mark.</hi> 16</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ioh.</hi> 21.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Hiſtoricall.</item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ioſu.</hi> 24.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iud.</hi> 21.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ruth.</hi> 4.</item>
                           <item>1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 31.</item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.</item>
                           <item>1. <hi>King.</hi> 22</item>
                           <item>2. <hi>King.</hi> 25</item>
                           <item>1. <hi>Cro.</hi> 29.</item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Cro.</hi> 36.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Nehe.</hi> 13.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Eſter.</hi> 10.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>New</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Acts.</hi> 24.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Sapientall.</item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iob.</hi> 42.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Pſal.</hi> 150.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Pro.</hi> 31.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Can.</hi> 8.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>New</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.</item>
                           <item>1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.</item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Collo.</hi> 4.</item>
                           <item>1. <hi>Theſ</hi> 5.</item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.</item>
                           <item>1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.</item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Phile.</hi> 1.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.</item>
                           <item>1. <hi>Pet</hi> 5.</item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.</item>
                           <item>1. <hi>Io.</hi> 5.</item>
                           <item>1. <hi>Io.</hi> 1.</item>
                           <item>3. <hi>Io.</hi> 1.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iude.</hi> 1.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Propheticall.</item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iſay</hi> 66.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iere.</hi> 52.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ezec.</hi> 48.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Dani.</hi> 12.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Hoſea.</hi> 14.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ioel.</hi> 4.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Amos.</hi> 6.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Obedi.</hi> 1.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ioſuah</hi> 4.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Micha.</hi> 7.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Nahum.</hi> 3</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Habac.</hi> 3.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Zepha</hi> 3.3</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Hagg.</hi> 2.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>New</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Reuel.</hi> 22.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <div n="1" type="argument">
               <pb facs="tcp:3176:8"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3176:8"/>
               <head>The Contents or ſumme <hi>of the firſt part.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe firſt part is called <hi>Legall,</hi> becauſe it <hi>chieflie containeth the law and ſtatutes of God the Creator to all his Creatures: in this order giuen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To things not hauing life, as the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement,</hi> the <hi>Earth,</hi> the <hi>Sea,</hi> &amp;c. Gen. 1.11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16.</p>
               <p>To things hauing life, as <hi>Foules, Fiſhes, Beaſts,</hi> &amp;c. 14, 25.</p>
               <p>To <hi>Adam</hi> before his fall, &amp; after <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 15, 16.3.15, 17, 19.</p>
               <p>To his poſteritie, in two <hi>Tables</hi> of ſtone written by the finger of GOD. <hi>Exod.</hi> 19, 20, 34.</p>
               <p>To the ſanctified members of Chriſt in the fleſhlie <hi>Tables</hi> of their hearts. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="argument">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:3176:9"/>
               <head>The Contents or ſumme <hi>of the ſecond part.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe ſecond part is called <hi>Hiſtoricall.</hi> for that therein is principallie ſette foorth manie and ſinguler examples of Gods mightie power, in protecting the lot of his inheritance: who, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <hi>Sathan</hi> and the world craftelie and cruellie reſiſteth; yet by a few ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple men, and of no reputation; hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed all the world with the ſweete ſound of Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne: and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrew their Conſpiracies, their Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries, their crueltie and outrage. In theſe Stories he hath left perfect notice to all the world, that hee neuer ſuffered them that truſted in him to periſh; nor
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3176:9"/> ſuch as delighted in their owne Armes to preuaile. Beſides, he hath in theſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Actions and Stories, as it were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred a perpetuall memorie to the Church: that the Croſſe is ordeined as an inſeparable companion to a good Chriſtian, which neuertheleſſe, is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in ſhort time, to endles and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable ioye: for ſo is the will of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="argument">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:3176:10"/>
               <head>The Contents of ſumme <hi>of the third part.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe third parte, which is <hi>Sapiental</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehendeth matter of great doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine concerning true Religion &amp; holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of life: it doth allure the hearts of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the diligent reading of Gods word, which is left as moſt precious Iewels to the Church. It deſcribeth the dee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable vanities of this worlde, that men ſhould not be addicted to anie thing in the ſame; but rather enflamed with the deſire of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly life &amp; bliſſe in Chriſt. It ſheweth forth by many ſweet &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant <hi>Allegories,</hi> ſimilitudes, parables, and compariſons, the perfect loue of Ieſus Chriſt in the creation and redemption. It teacheth vs to tread in the ſteps and pathes of the true Church, whoſe affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions are enflamed with pure bountie &amp; loue of the <hi>Meſsiah,</hi> who is become ours, by taking our nature vpon him, and by accompliſhing al things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to our Saluation and Redemption.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="argument">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:3176:10"/>
               <head>The Contents, or ſomme of the <hi>fourth part.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe 4. part, which is Propheticall,</hi> interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the lawe contained brieflie in two Tables. It foretelleth manie notable things touching the promiſe of the Meſsiah, his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, his kingdom, the fauor of God towards his Church, and the perſwaſion that is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with <hi>Iaphet</hi> to dwell in the houſe of <hi>Sem</hi> as God had ſaid vnto <hi>Noah.</hi> It directeth all men to the aſſurance of Gods eternall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, by the conſideration of things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, paſt, and to come; whereof the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets are plentifull.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <p>By obſeruing this order, you ſhall be able to iudge neerelie where euerie matter that commeth in your hearing doth lie in the Bible, or what ſcripture ſoeuer you ſhal read elſewhere. For all things profitable to our inſtruction and ſaluation is contained in the foure parts before recited: therefore marke how they are diſtinguiſhed.</p>
            <p>Firſt, learne how the whole is diuided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>9. Periods,</hi> or ſtories. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dlie, where eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <hi>Period</hi> or ſtorie doo begin and end in the Bible. Thirdlie, that you learne to ſay ſome
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3176:11"/> thing as the holy Ghoſt vttereth concerning the <hi>Creation</hi> in Gen. 1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>The Flood,</hi> Gen. 7, 8. <hi>The Promiſe,</hi> Gen. 12. <hi>The gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the law,</hi> Exod. 19, 20. <hi>The going out of Aegypt,</hi> Exod. 12, 13, 14. <hi>Their entrance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Canaan,</hi> Ioſua. 1, 2, 3. <hi>Their poſſeſſion,</hi> 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19. <hi>The firſt King,</hi> 1. Sam. 9, 10. <hi>The Captiuitie,</hi> the booke of <hi>Daniel,</hi> 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8. <hi>Their libertie in Chriſt,</hi> Matth. 1, 2, 27, 28. The continuance of euerie pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod or ſtorie I haue laid downe at the end of euerie one ſuch. Be ſure to obſerue this order.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. From the <hi>Creation</hi> to the <hi>Flood</hi> Gen. 1. to Gen. 7, a ſtorie of 1656. yeares.</item>
               <item>2. From the <hi>Flood</hi> to the promiſe firſt to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bram</hi> Gen. 8, to Gen. 12, a ſtorie of 427. yeares.</item>
               <item>3. From the <hi>Promiſe</hi> made to <hi>Abram</hi> to the giuing of the lawe Gen. 12. to Exod. 19, a ſtorie of 430. yeares.</item>
               <item>4. From <hi>their going out of Aegypt</hi> to their entrance into <hi>Canaan</hi> Exod. 12, to Ioſua 1, a ſtorie of 40. yeares.</item>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:3176:11"/>
               <item>5. From their <hi>entrance into Canaan</hi> to their <hi>quiet poſſeſſion. Ioſua 1,</hi> to <hi>Iudges 1,</hi> a Storie of 7. yeares.</item>
               <item>6. From their <hi>quiet poſſeſſion</hi> to <hi>Saule their first King. Iudg. 1.</hi> to the <hi>1. Sam. 1,</hi> a Storie of 450. yeares.</item>
               <item>7. From <hi>Saule their firſt King,</hi> to the <hi>Captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. 1. Sam.</hi> to <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> a Storie of 490. yeares.</item>
               <item>8. From their <hi>captiuitie</hi> to their <hi>libertie,</hi> theſe bookes, <hi>Nehemiah, Ezra, Hester:</hi> a Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of 70. yeares.</item>
               <item>9. From their <hi>libertie</hi> vnto <hi>Chriſt</hi> the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting libertie: the booke of <hi>Daniel</hi> a Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of 490. yeares.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe things being well &amp; perfectly ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled in your minde, then conſider <hi>what is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in euerie Period</hi> particularly, I meane what the Argument or Summe of euerie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch Storie is: whereby you ſhall ſee where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon the <hi>Bible</hi> doth depend, what <hi>Religion</hi> was in euerie Age, the <hi>cauſe of the alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3176:12"/> which you muſt doo aduiſedly in this order.</p>
            <div n="1" type="period">
               <head>1. PERIOD.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>In euerie</hi> Period <hi>marke what is ſaid of</hi> God the Creator <hi>in this order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Creator</hi> called himſelfe in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue tongue <hi>Iehouah,</hi> whom in our language we cal <hi>God, Gen. 1, 1. Deu. 6.4.</hi> It is a name of wonderfull weight &amp; vnſearchable conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and yet not anſwerable to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his Maieſtie, in reſpect of his deuine perſon and godly eſſence. It conteineth fiue <hi>vowells,</hi> which are the ground and perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all languages: for, as without the ſame no tongue can be diſtinct or vnderſtood, ſo without the true knowledge and loue of his eternall Maieſtie, no man can ſpeake vnto him rightly: all will be but babling, or as though hee vnderſtood it not. This name hath in it alſo 2. <hi>h. h.</hi> which in all languages are nothing els but aſpiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or breathings, thereby making vp the number of 7. letters, being the full number of the Sabaoth, allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this ſaying, <hi>From him wee haue our breathing, in him we liue, moue, and haue our being.</hi> For we are his generation, <hi>Act. 17.28.</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:3176:12"/> And alſo to teach that the praiſing of God is a part of the ſanctification of the Sabaoth, without the which, no ſoule hath reſt or peace with God.</p>
               <q>Iehouah our God.</q>
               <p>Marke the force of this word <hi>Our:</hi> It is not attributed to the Father, nor to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghoſt, but directly to the Sonne of the Father, who is become <hi>ours</hi> &amp; we his, <hi>Cant. 2.16.</hi> by taking our nature vpon him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the vſe and interest of all his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, together with the worke of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, he hath left this exerciſe for euer in his Sanctuarie, ſaying;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Praiſe me the eternall God:</hi> which is the ſignification of this holy name <hi>Iehouah,</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring vs alſo thereby of his aeternall fauor, in whom is no ſhadow of change: for <hi>what he was, the ſame he is, and will be to come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He hath many other names in respect of his qualitie &amp; rich liberalitie towards his Saints, and in regard of his iuſtice towards the reprobate. <hi>As</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:3176:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Palmoni, Michael, &amp;c.</hi> Of the ſame num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of letters, but of three vowels, pointing cloſely to the vnitie of the <hi>Trinitie.</hi> The one ſignifieth that he numbreth &amp; finiſheth the liuings and liues of al men, that he weigheth all mens words and workes in a ballance or waight of the Sanctuarie, that he diuideth and giueth how he wil, and to whom it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him. <hi>Dan. 5.26, 27, 28.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Michael</hi> ſignifieth verie God, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that there is no other: he is God alone. <hi>Michael</hi> is only thriſe repeated in Scripture, Dan. 10.21. Dan. 12.1. Iudg. 1.9. <hi>There is no Angell of that name.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <head>Wherein we are to conſider 4. things.</head>
                  <item>His Wiſedome in creating all good.</item>
                  <item>His Power in gouerning all his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</item>
                  <item>His Prouidence in prouiding all good things for his.</item>
                  <item>His Iuſtice in deſtroying all the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:3176:13"/>
               <p>In euerie ſtorie or <hi>Period</hi> you ſhall ſee theſe particulars, which will further your purpoſe, and put you in mind of diuers other ſuch like concerning GOD: whereby you ſhall bee perfect in that accompt, which is the firſt and principall poynt required of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie Chriſtian. Then obſerue whereſoeuer you reade, what is ſpoken of GOD, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell cols="2">3. in one </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26, 27.18.2, 3, 9, 10.13.16 17, 20, 21, 22, 23, 26, 27. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.30. 1. Timo. 3, 16. Ephe. 4, 5.6.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell rows="3">Or 1. in 3. diſtinct</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Father.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Gene. 1.1, 2, 3. Matt. 3.16, 17.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Sonne.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Gen. 1, 3. Mat. 3.16.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Holie Ghoſt.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Gen. 1.2. Matt. 3, 16.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument or ſomme of this firſt <hi>Period.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Reade Gen. the 5. there you ſhall ſee <hi>10. holie Fathers,</hi> which I haue laid downe in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3176:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> their order, in whom the Church of GOD ſtood, who as skilfull Muſitians, did ſweetly ſing one ſong, making a heauenlie ſound o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all the world, whoſe liues were ended at the flood, whoſe holie Religion hath ende with the fire, the reward of whoſe labours hath eternall memorie with GOD and his Angells, which are theſe that followe, with their ſignifications and yeares.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell role="label">Fathers.</cell>
                           <cell role="label">
                              <hi>Significations.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="label" cols="2">Yeares.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Adam</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>earthlie.</cell>
                           <cell>930</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.5,</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Seth</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>ſetled.</cell>
                           <cell>912</cell>
                           <cell>8,</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Enos</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>ſorowfull.</cell>
                           <cell>905</cell>
                           <cell>11,</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Kenan</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>godly repentance.</cell>
                           <cell>910</cell>
                           <cell>14,</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Mahalael</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>praiſe God.</cell>
                           <cell>895</cell>
                           <cell>17,</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Iared</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>the lowly.</cell>
                           <cell>962</cell>
                           <cell>20,</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Henoch</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>the Sabaoth keeper.</cell>
                           <cell>365</cell>
                           <cell>24,</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Methuſelah</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>long life.</cell>
                           <cell>969</cell>
                           <cell>27,</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Lamech</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>heart wounded.</cell>
                           <cell>777</cell>
                           <cell>33.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Noah.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>the comforter.</cell>
                           <cell>950</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.29</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>This number of <hi>10. Fathers,</hi> wherin God hath meaſured his <hi>Church,</hi> ſerueth very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily to expound hard ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the ſame nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber. But you muſt marke that <hi>10.</hi> ſometimes ſtandeth in good part, as in Tithes, <hi>Leui. 27.32. Nu. 18.25, 26, 27, 28.</hi>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:3176:14"/> In the <hi>10.</hi> moneth the flood abated <hi>Gen. 8.5.</hi> God would haue ſpared manie thouſands for 10. ſake, <hi>Gen. 18.42. &amp;c.</hi> Sometimes 10. is taken in accompt of euill, as <hi>Numb. 14.22. Eſai. 5.10.</hi> Againe, <hi>10. hornes</hi> of the Beaſt which <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaw, ſignifieth 10. wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Kings, <hi>Dan. 7.24.</hi> The Pope hath 10. ſtatelie Kingdomes to aſsiſt him, <hi>Reuel. 13.1.</hi> Thus muſt you compare one 10. with another as you reade.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>Now marke brieflie the ſtorie of euerie Father particularlie, in the which you may, by compariſon, expound other places of like qualitie in Scriptures.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ADam,</hi> his originall or kinred was the red earth of <hi>Moriah,</hi> nere the garden of <hi>Eden</hi> a mount in <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Where <hi>Iſaac</hi> was offered, as a figure of Chriſt the holie of holieſt. <hi>Gen. 22 2.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Where <hi>Sem,</hi> or <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> dwelt, which place was called <hi>Salem,</hi> but vppon <hi>Iſaac</hi> his offering, it was called <hi>Ieruſalem. Gen. 14.18.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Where <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke reſted in the threſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing place of <hi>Araunah</hi> the <hi>Jebuſite. 2. Sam. 24. 16, 17, 18,</hi> to <hi>25.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Where <hi>Salomon</hi> was commanded to build
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3176:15"/> the Temple. <hi>2. Chro. 3.1.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Where was the Oratorie of God, the law and the ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>Where Chriſt in the ſulnes of time died, as a high <hi>Sacrificer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Marke euerie Moriah as you reade, and conferre one with another by particular questions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Adam</hi> was in ſoule a Saint for wiſedome and will.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>So are all his posteritie in Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He was a <hi>King,</hi> a <hi>Prophet,</hi> and a <hi>Sacrificer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>So was Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And it is certain that he beleeued the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe concerning Chriſt, in whoſe comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration he offered continuall ſacrifice, the which was conſumed by fire from heauen in the allowance thereof, as was the ſacrifice of <hi>Abram, &amp;c.</hi> in the time of the Lawe. In the aſſurance whereof he named his wife <hi>Heua,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>life.</hi> And he called his Sonne <hi>Seth, ſetled</hi> or <hi>perſwaded</hi> in Chriſt. Hee brought vp his Sonnes <hi>Abel</hi> and <hi>Cain</hi> in the ſame profeſsion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By faith</hi> Abel <hi>offered a greater ſacrifice than</hi> Cain, <hi>by the which he obtained witneſſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3176:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> that he was righteous, God teſtifying of his gifts. Hab. 11.4.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>God cloathed <hi>Adam</hi> &amp; his wife with the skinnes of thoſe beaſts which hee had ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>The firſt promiſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                     </label> 
                  </p>
                  <p>When God had <hi>chaſtened the woman</hi> and <hi>curſed the ſerpent.</hi> He ſaid vnto <hi>Adam, The ſeed of the woman ſhall bruſe the ſerpents head. Gen. 3.15.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He liued with <hi>Methuſalah</hi> to inſtruct him in this promiſe, and in the right vſe thereof 243. yeares as in <hi>Gen. 5.25, 26, 27, 32.6.6.11.10, 11.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He was skilfull in all Sciences the firſt day, and 30. yeare of age, by the vſe of nature as men are now.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>So was Chriſt at the end of </hi>Daniels<hi> laſt weeke 9, when he was baptized </hi>Lu. 2.23.</p>
                  <p>And it muſt needes ſtand by manie argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and plaine narrations, that he fell the the ſame day of his creation.</p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:3176:16"/>
                  <p>His Wife was a goodlie, faire, and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Queene.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>So is the Wife of Chriſt, the Church, all glorious, and there is no ſpot within her.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus by particular obſeruations, you may make your compariſon fit with other places of the ſame ſenſe out of the olde or new.</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>Read</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mat. 19.4, 5, 6.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mark 10.3, 4, 5, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chriſt comes of</hi> Adam, <hi>Rom. 5.1. 1. Cor. 15.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A compariſon betweene Chriſt and</hi> Adam. <hi>1. Tim. 2. Reuel. 12.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SEth</hi> was the 3. ſonne of <hi>Adam,</hi> begotten in the likenes of his Father, when hee was 130. yeare olde. All the world is bound to take inſtruction of him, to be ſetled in Chriſt the Rocke. All places of Scripture that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the Rocke Chriſt, ſetled faith and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie may be reduced vnto this.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The number </hi>130.<hi> in which he was begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, ſerueth verie well to remember you of al places of the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> number in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. </hi>As</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:3176:16"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Terah</hi> begat <hi>Abram,</hi> a newe Stabliſher of Religion when he was 130. yeare olde.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jaacob</hi> came to <hi>Aegipt,</hi> a Reuiuer of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion when he was 130. yeare olde.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You ſhall reade ſeldome, or but once, in </hi>Luk. 3.38.<hi> of </hi>Seth<hi> in the New Testament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ENos</hi> was verie zealous and ſorrowfull for the corruption of Religion and good manners, which was like to enſue vppon the marriage of the ſonnes of GOD with the daughters of men, who regarded beautie and worldlie preferment, rather than the promiſes of life and euerlaſting glorie, by ſeruing and praiſing God in true Religion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To this you may referre the zeale of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Elias, Paule, Iohn, &amp;c.</hi> who wept for the people that ſinned, and deſired rather to bee razed out of the booke of life, than that ſo manie thouſands ſhould periſh in the wrath of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To this you may referre all vnequall and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate mariages, and the inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that commeth thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:3176:17"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>KEnan</hi> had ſorowfulnes and withall god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie repentance, furniſhed with a care of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To this you may reduce all penitent ſinners, as </hi>Dauid, Peter,<hi> &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MAhalael</hi> had a name verie anſwerable to that acceptable Sacrifice which the Creator impoſed vppon his creation, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſignification of his owne name: both which I haue told you.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To this may be reduced all places of thanks giuing and praiſing of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So <hi>Leah</hi> named her fourth ſonne, <hi>Iudah,</hi> ſigniſying, <hi>praiſe the Lord.</hi> This ought to be imitated of all men throughout the courſe of Religion and trade of life. <hi>Pſal. 47.</hi> The reaſon why, is ſhewed <hi>Pſal. 19.102, 105.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IAred</hi> had the vertues of his forefathers, which induced him to great humilitie and lowlines.</p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:3176:17"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To this you may referre all ſuch like places, how God exalteth the lowlie and meeke.</hi> As</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Joſeph</hi> out of the pit of ſlyme, to be Lord and ruler in all the Land of <hi>Aegipt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dauid</hi> a poore ſimple Shepheard, to be a renowmed king ouer his inheritance, and <hi>Daniel</hi> &amp; <hi>Peter, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This muſt needes call you to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the proud and their ouerthrow vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the dunghill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>HEnoch walked with God in holie life, he was a man wholly dedicated to the Lord by his name &amp; in the trade of his life, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in was ſeene his fathers zeale and ſound Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in bringing him vp meete for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the great God, as <hi>Abram</hi> did <hi>Jſaac.</hi> as <hi>Anna</hi> did <hi>Samuel, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He was faithfull.</hi> Read <hi>Haebr:</hi> 11.5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He was a Prophet.</hi> Iude. 1.14, 15.</p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:3176:18"/>
                  <p>He is the ſeauenth from <hi>Adam,</hi> his yeares are agreeable with the number of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth, putting all men in minde of the ſixe dayes creation, and the ſeauenth dayes Reſt or redemption. Seauen is an holy and an infinite number importing grace &amp; peace by <hi>Ieſus Chriſt. Leuiticus.</hi> 25.8, 9, 10, 11. Seuen eyes in the <hi>Reuelation</hi> ſignifieth Gods ſeuen folde &amp; incomprehenſible wiſedome and prouidence.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The </hi>number of 7.<hi> is alſo taken, manie times, for a time certaine, and ceaſing in euillpart, as </hi>Nabuchadnezzar<hi> was a beaſt </hi>7.<hi> yeres &amp; no longer. The </hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle<hi> was </hi>7.<hi> moneths in building, and no longer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sometimes 7. is in good part, and for a certeine time ceaſing, as the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> was 7. yeres in conquering.</p>
                  <p>All notable actions were done in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall number of 7. from <hi>Moſes</hi> to Chriſt his death by 7. ſeauens. Seueh fifties for the glorie of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> houſe. Seuen ſeuenties for the houſe of <hi>Iudah.</hi> Seuen tennes for the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3176:18"/> captiuitie. Seuen ſeuenties to Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thus you ſhal make vſe of </hi>ſeuen<hi> in al actions throughout the holie Bible.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The holie ſeruants of God, as a rare mark to behold, were borne in the equall number of 7. As
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Henoch</hi> the 7. from <hi>Adam.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Heber</hi> the 7. from <hi>Henoch.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Iſaac</hi> the 7. from <hi>Heber.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Moſes</hi> the 7. from <hi>Abram.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ioſua</hi> the 7. from <hi>Ephraim</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ioram</hi> the 7. from <hi>Dauid.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MEthuſelah</hi> hauing all the vertues and bleſsings of his forefathers, after his death ſhal haue life aeternal which his name did teach him by the ſignification thereof. As <hi>Adam</hi> liued 249. yeres to inſtruct him; ſo he liued with <hi>Sem</hi> to teach him 98. yeres.</p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:3176:19"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Applie this to the faithfull, as a reward of their labours in Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>His age was an exact number or rule of the Flood, the waters could not drowne the world while he liued.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The like may be ſaid of </hi>Lot,<hi> that fire could not fall vppon </hi>Sodome,<hi> vntill he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into </hi>Zoar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LAmech</hi> he was outwardlie afflicted by men, &amp; inwardlie afflicted in conſcience by the diuell: he was a Prophet for he ſpake of things manie hundred yeares paſt, and of the comfort that ſhould fall out by <hi>Woah. Gen. 5.28, 29.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A fit reſemblance of the Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>NOah</hi> found grace and fauour in the ſight of God, in him was eſtabliſhed the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant made to <hi>Adam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:3176:19"/>
                  <p>His houſehold, as a ſmall remnant left in the Arke, is leſt as an equall portion of the ſmalnes of the Church, in reſpect of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Doue,</hi> bringing an Oliue leafe, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified peace and plentie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You may compare it wel with the holie Ghoſt bringing glad tidings and euerlasting ioy to the Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He was the <hi>10</hi> from <hi>Adam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Remember 10.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Reade for <hi>Noah, Matt. 24. Luk. 17. Hab. 11. 1. Pet. 3. 2. Pet. 2.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſignification of their names being wel lincked and chained together, makes vp a Chriſtian Sacrifice and the whole ſomme of Religion brieflie thus.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Maiestie of God</hi> foreſeeing the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> gaue him a name anſwerable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, which was <hi>Earthly, miſerable, periſhing, dying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Adam</hi> finding the ſame true in him and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3176:20"/> in his poſteritie, he comprehended by the light of Gods ſpirit, that the ſeed of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhould reſtore him and all beleeuers into the fauour of God, and therfore he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his third ſonne <hi>Seth;</hi> which is in our lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage <hi>ſetled, perſwaded,</hi> &amp; <hi>reſolued in Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seth</hi> was in his profeſsion and trade of life as his name ſignified: and becauſe he knew that to be ſetled in Chriſt cannot bee without contrition and griefe for ſinne, he named his ſonne <hi>Enos, ſorowfull:</hi> the rather becauſe ſorowful corruption began to grow by the mariage of the daughters of men.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Enos</hi> knowing that there was two ſorts of ſorowe or repentance, a godly &amp; a world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie; therefore he named his ſonne <hi>Kenan, godlie repentance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Kenan</hi> being ſetled in Chriſt, ſorowfull for ſinne, and hauing godlie repentance, he named his ſonne the <hi>praiſe God,</hi> in Hebrue <hi>Mahalael.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mahalael,</hi> hauing in himſelfe al the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer vertues, he called his ſonne <hi>lared, lowlie,</hi> without the which all is ſinne.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:3176:20"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iared,</hi> knowing that the ſanctification of the Sabaoth is a degree of vertue, and a great peece of this ſpirituall Sacrifice, he called his ſonne <hi>Henoch,</hi> the <hi>Sabaoth keeper.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Henoch,</hi> to ſet foorth the reward of all thoſe excellent vertues, named his ſonne <hi>Methuſelah,</hi> that is, <hi>long life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Methuſelah,</hi> knowing well that the Church in the meane time ſhould endure manie tribulations, he called his ſonne <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mech,</hi> which is by interpretation, <hi>hart woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lamech,</hi> although his caſe, and his brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren profeſsing Ieſus Chriſt was wretched and full of hart woundes, yet after a while they ſhould reioyce, and in token thereof he called his ſonne <hi>Noah, a Comforter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Goe backward or forward, he that hath one of theſe vertues hath all; they cannot bee ſeperated: he that miſſeth of one miſſeth of all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He that is ſetled in Chriſt is ſorowfull for his ſinne; he that is ſorowfull, is godlie
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3176:21"/> ſorowfull vnto repentance: he that hath à godlie repentance, praiſeth God in pouertie and in plentie: he that praiſeth GOD, is lowlie in all eſtates: he that is lowlie, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the Sabaoth: he that ſanctifieth the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth, ſhal haue long life: he that hath theſe former vertues, ſhall be hartelie wounded in this world: but in the world to come he ſhall haue ioye and comfort, which no man ſhall take from him.</p>
                  <p>He that keepeth not the ioy of Chriſt in his heart, is not heartelie wounded: he that is not wounded and in afflictions here, hath no hope of long life: he that hopeth not for long life, keepeth not the Sabaoth: he that keepeth not the Sabaoth, is not lowlie: he that is not lowlie, praiſeth not God: he that praiſeth not GOD, hath not godlie repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: he that hath not godlie repentance, is not ſorowfull: he that is not ſorowfull, is not ſetled on Chriſt the rocke, but is earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, miſerable, periſhing, &amp;c.</p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:3176:21"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now marke who were enemies in their time.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Serpent</hi> a lier. <hi>Gen. 3.1, 2, 3 4, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Kain</hi> a murther. <hi>Gen. 4.1, 2, 3 4, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Lamech</hi> an adulterer. <hi>Gene. 4.18, 19, 20. &amp;c</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>By <hi>lying,</hi> pride entred.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>pride,</hi> murther iſſued.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>fleſhlie luſt,</hi> contempt of Religion followed.</p>
                  <p>Theſe 6. were the ſinnes of the old world, the earth was corrupt, and filled with the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normitie thereof. <hi>Gen. 6.5, 6, 7, 11, 12, 13.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaketh much of theſe ſinners in thoſe daies. 22.15, 16, 17. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.19, 20. <hi>Jude</hi> 1. 14, 15.</p>
                  <p>1 The <hi>Serpent</hi> was a goodlie faire crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but verie wiſe and ſubtill. <hi>Matth. 10.16.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:3176:22"/>
                  <p>The <hi>Angells</hi> ſeeing the excellencie of the creation day by day, &amp; perceiuing that they and all creatures els were made but as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to <hi>Adam,</hi> they preſentlie vppon his creation murmured, and were not content with their eſtate; but left their habitation and calling, which made GOD to reſerue them in euerlaſting chaines. <hi>Iud. 1.6.</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon hee preſentlie fell to tempt <hi>Adam,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3.</p>
                  <p>The head of theſe euill Spirits was <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer;</hi> as hee was more cleare and brighter than other Angells, ſo he fell into a more filthie Apoſtacie: he was not euill by kind, but of his owne aduiſement he turned out of kind: he fell willingly, as <hi>Adam</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good into euill, from light into darknes: he coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted highnes not meete for him: therefore he was throwne into the loweſt place: he with an infinite multitude more were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of their beautie and glorie. They were at the firſt heauenlie bodies: but vpon their fall they were turned into the qualitie of the ayre.</p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:3176:22"/>
                  <p>Theſe were called by diuers names an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to their kinde and qualitie.</p>
                  <p>Whereof 4. are in the 12. chap. and .9. verſ. of the <hi>Reuelation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>a Deuill.</hi> For that hee is a quareller, a callenger and a backbiter.</item>
                     <item>2 <hi>a Dragon.</hi> In reſpect of his wonderfull crueltie and ſpeedie ſpoile.</item>
                     <item>3 <hi>a Sathan.</hi> For that hee is a Tempter, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.10. Aduerſarie or ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.31, 32. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4, 4. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2, 18. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3, 5.2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.9, 10. <hi>Reu.</hi> 2.13.</item>
                     <item>4 <hi>a Serpent.</hi> For his ſubtiltie and craft. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11, 3.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Behemoth,</hi> is likened to an Oxe: for that he laboureth and enforceth all his power to drawe men to deſtruction. <hi>Iob.</hi> 40, 10.</p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:3176:23"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Leuiathan,</hi> a great mightie fiſh, not to be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with line and hooke; ſo the Diuell cannot bee meeked and tamed by the nature of man. <hi>Iob.</hi> 40.20.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lion,</hi> who is verie rauening, and alway ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth with his eyes open, moſt watchful and vigilant: ſo the diuell ſeeking who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he may deuoure. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Boare,</hi> for his rooting, extirpation, vtter ſubuerſion and deſtruction. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80.13</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now I will ſpeake briefly of thoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, which were left in heauen, and continued in their first Eſtate, of whom you ſhall read much in holy Scriptures, and of their ſundrie names in respect of their ſeuerall &amp; ſundrie offices in the Church, and in heauen: which I pray you diligenly to marke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N Angell</hi> is a name of office &amp; not of kinde. He is of a ſpirituall &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall ſubſtance, and of great puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3176:23"/> by reaſon whereof he perceiueth in him ſelfe all formes &amp; ſhapes intelligible, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he is ſtirred to heauenly contemplations. The likeneſſe of GOD ſhineth in him. <hi>Haeb.</hi> 1.7.</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>Angels haue three things in them.</head>
                     <item>1 <hi>Eſſence:</hi> by the which they haue beeing of puritie, of diſcretion, and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Vertue:</hi> by the which they haue power to vnderſtand, to liue, and to continue for euer.</item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Working:</hi> by the which they are exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to doo all things ſwiſtly, willingly, and profitably to Gods glorie, and to the benefite of his Church.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <label>Angels called Seraphins.</label> BEcauſe they are manie, they are inflamed with the cleare light and brightneſſe of God: their office is to kindle and inflame
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3176:24"/> others in the loue of God. This fire where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they are kindled; burneth and not wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth. <hi>Haeb.</hi> 1, 14.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Angels are called Cherubins.</label> A Companie or a multitude higher than the <hi>Seraphins:</hi> theſe haue the gift of fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the firſt vertue that worketh. For by the light of wiſedome they be drawen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the faireneſſe of GOD himſelfe. <hi>Haeb.</hi> 9, 5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Angels called Thrones.</label> THe Maieſtie of God ſitteth in and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon theſe. Their offices is to ſet foorth GODS Iuſtice againſt vnpenitent ſinners. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 14.17, 18, 19, 20. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 80.1. <hi>Cherubins</hi> and <hi>Thrones</hi> are one.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Angels called Dominations.</label> THeſe are aboue the reſt in power, they haue Iuſtice in force, libertie in godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and they conforme all their actions to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3176:24"/> The rule and direction of their Preſident. <hi>Haebr.</hi> 1, 6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Angels called Principalities.</label> THeir office is to bring and reduce others to God. They are ouer other Angells. Some of them ſerue, and ſome waite. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9, 10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.7.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Angels called Powers.</label> FOr that they haue power ouer euill An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and wicked ſpirites. Their office is, to keepe &amp; comfort the Saints on the earth. Theſe haue equal might with thoſe Angels which are called <hi>Dominations. Reuel.</hi> 16.1, 2, 3, 4, 7, 8, 9, 10. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3, 22.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All theſe are ſaid to be</hi> cloathed with fire, and with Light, as with a garment. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They</hi> are girded with a golden Girdle, <hi>ſignifying might and courage.</hi> Dan. 10 5. Reuel. 15, 6.</p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:3176:25"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They beare in their hands</hi> ſwords <hi>&amp;</hi> ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. <hi>A</hi> ſword <hi>to rule, and a</hi> ſcepter <hi>to magnifie.</hi> Gen. 3.24. Numb. 22.31. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſua 5, 13. Reuel. 6.8. <hi>warlike weapons, fighting for the Church ſpiritually.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They haue</hi> Trowels, Meaſures, <hi>and all ſorts of working tooles, to worke men a new vnto God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They haue</hi> Trumpets, <hi>for that they warne and excite men to heare the voyce of God, and to prepare themſelues againſt the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall enemie.</hi> Reuel. 8, 2.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They haue</hi> Inſtruments of Muſique, <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting and refreſhing the weake &amp; wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, as was ſignified by the Leuites.</hi> 2. Cron. 7, 6. Reuel. 5.8, 18, 22.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They are likened to</hi> Horſes <hi>of all coulours, to</hi> Chariots, <hi>and to</hi> Eagles, <hi>for that they are poasts and ſpeedie meſſengers betwixt Christ and his Church.</hi> Ierem. 4, 13. Zachar. 1.8, 9. 6.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. Reuel. 9.16, 17.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They are likened to</hi> Warders, <hi>and vnto</hi>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:3176:25"/> Watchmen, <hi>for that they forewarne the Church of perills.</hi> Pſal. 141, 3. Eſa. 21.6, 7, 8, 9. Ierem. 51, 12. Dan. 4, 10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They are likened to</hi> Harueſters <hi>and</hi> Labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,<hi>for that they gather men into the Lordes Barne, as wheate.</hi> Ierem. 50, 16. Mich. 7, 1. Math. 9.37, 38.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They are called by manie other names, and likened to diuers naturall things, thereby to make vs the better to diſcerne them, the plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier to ſee them, and the eaſier to auoide that which maie diſlike them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Marke them well, and reduce them by particulars into memorie, which will greatly profite you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>THE particular Ages and Yeares of the <hi>ten Fathers, Gen. 5.</hi> before recited ſerueth as an exact rule to knowe howe long the <hi>first Storie or Period,</hi> and the world of olde did laſt.</p>
                  <p>The ſame manifeſteth vnto all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the louing kindneſſe of the Lord, who as yet in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> hee gaue them, one hundred and twentie Yeares
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3176:26"/> Repentance and withal the ſeueritie of God in making the earth voide and emptie, as it was in the beginning becauſe of ſinne: &amp; in not <hi>ſuffering the posteritie of</hi> Noah <hi>to liue halfe their former yeares:</hi> which was a noate of Gods Iuſtice to the wicked in breaking their earthly imaginations: and a teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of his loue towards his elect, by haſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their kingdome and glorie.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="period">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:3176:26"/>
               <head>2. PERIOD.</head>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument or ſumme of the <hi>2. Period.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>REade <hi>Gen. 11.</hi> there God in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of other <hi>10. holie Fathers,</hi> begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to multiplie a new Church; ouer whom he was verie carefull and prouident, as of a peculiar and ſpeciall people dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his owne glorie, and ſequeſtred from ill and prophane vſes; which I haue laide downe in their order, with the ſignifications of their <hi>names</hi> and <hi>yeares,</hi> which you ſhall perceiue ſerueth to great purpoſe.</p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:3176:27"/>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell role="label">Fathers.</cell>
                           <cell role="label">
                              <hi>Significations.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="label">Yeares.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1 <hi>Sem</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>renowmed.</cell>
                           <cell>600. <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.11.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>2 <hi>Arphaxad</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>healing.</cell>
                           <cell>438. <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.13.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>3 <hi>Sale</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>peace</cell>
                           <cell>433. <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.15.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>4 <hi>Heber</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>pilgrime.</cell>
                           <cell>464. <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.17.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>5 <hi>Peleg</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>diuided.</cell>
                           <cell>209. <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.19.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>6 <hi>Regue</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>breaking.</cell>
                           <cell>207. <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.21.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>7 <hi>Sarug</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>palme trees.</cell>
                           <cell>200. <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.23.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>8 <hi>Nahor</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>angrie or drie.</cell>
                           <cell>119. <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.25.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>9 <hi>Terah</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>a wretch.</cell>
                           <cell>70. <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.26.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>10 <hi>Abram.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>a high father.</cell>
                           <cell>175. <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.7.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>Now you muſt learne what may be ſaid particularlie of theſe Fathers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sem</hi> was <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> King of <hi>Salem,</hi> who liued 600. yeres, who was <hi>Noahs</hi> Sonne.</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:3176:27"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SEm</hi> was a perfect figure of Chriſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out father &amp; without mother, in reſpect of his great age, whoſe kindred was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to any man, when <hi>Lot</hi> was taken priſoner, for he was before the flood, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a Graundfather in <hi>Abram</hi> his time of eight degrees. At the ſlaughter of the Kings he might well bee renowmed; for when all Nations were at variance round about him, he was vnto them at <hi>Salem</hi> a ſight of <hi>peace,</hi> he ruled with great wiſedome and dexteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, like the Sonne of God; he outliued all that knew him. None of <hi>Chams</hi> houſe could reſemble the Sonne of God, nor any of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> houſe, whoſe Religion came from <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>The 2. promiſe concerning Chriſt.</label> 
                  </p>
                  <p>SAint <hi>Paule</hi> ment when he ſaid that <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech</hi> was without father and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mother, nothing els but to call the <hi>Iewes</hi> to minde, who (in their Storie) was the true figure of Chriſt, without father and without mother. <hi>Sem</hi> liued vntill 50. yeares of <hi>Jſaac</hi> his age, to teach Religion. <hi>Bleſſed be the God of Sem. Gen. 9.26.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:3176:28"/>
                  <p>Saint <hi>Paule</hi> chargeth men to conſider of him, &amp; to compare him with <hi>Abram,</hi> which cannot bee, if he bee indeede without father and mother. Read more <hi>Luk. 3. Haebr. 5.6.7.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Heber</hi> was a rare man, 2. ſeuens from the creation, a double <hi>Henoch,</hi> he was the 4 af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the flood.</p>
                  <p>So is <hi>Judah</hi> the 4. from <hi>Iaacob,</hi> of whom Chriſt came.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Marke alwaies the number 4. and make your compariſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Hebrew tongue remained in him, whence he had his name, at the confuſion of tongues, which enlarged his glorie. Againe, none that euer were before him, liued after him.</p>
                  <p>In his time <hi>Babel</hi> was built, by the curſe of <hi>Cham</hi> there they loſt the glorie of their name, which was turned to ſhame. Thence they were ſcattered ouer the world into 70. companies, where afterwards they were in bondage 70. yeares. <hi>There their ages were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine halfed the 2. time.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:3176:28"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To this you may referre the fall of Angells, who by pride ſurmounted aboue their Creator, ſeeking to enlarge their glorie, but thereby it was diminiſhed greatlie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The like may be ſaid of <hi>Adam,</hi> who co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueted to be ouer wiſe, became a verie foole, and coueting all, loſt all.</p>
                  <p>The like of <hi>Jſrael,</hi> who not contented with the Lord, deſired to be gouerned by man, had an hypocrite for their King.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abram</hi> was a new ſetter vp of Religion in his time, as was <hi>Seth</hi> in the old world; he was the 10. from <hi>Noah,</hi> and the 7. before <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſhewing therein, that in 10. he was on earth the higheſt accompt, and in 7. the holieſt by Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Here marke 10. and 7. and conferre them elſewhere with the like numbers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He ouercame foure Kings with his owne houſehold.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To this you may call to mind the conqueſt of <hi>Ioſua,</hi> who with a ſmall companie ſubdued mightie Nations; and eſpeciallie to Chriſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3176:29"/> Ieſus, who by himſelfe, conquered all the world and the power of Sathan to deliuer the Captiue.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He had the <hi>Promiſe</hi> concerning <hi>Canaan,</hi> and concerning Chriſt to come. God chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his name <hi>Abram,</hi> a high father, to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> a father of manie Nations; declaring thereby, the vnſearchable riches and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the father in Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Here Ages were the third time halfed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Reade more <hi>Ioh. 8. Luk. 16. Act. 7. Rom. 4. Haebr. 7.11. Matth. 1.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abram</hi> had two ſonnes, <hi>Iſmael</hi> and <hi>Iſaac: Iſaac</hi> was a ſonne by the free woman, which was borne by promiſe, who being offered &amp; not ſlaine, is a figure of Chriſt, who was kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and behold aliue. <hi>Reuel. 5.6.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abram</hi> is a figure of God the Father, who ſpared not his only ſonne. <hi>Jſaac</hi> is the longeſt liuer after <hi>Heber,</hi> and liued longer than his father, to ſhewe that he was the child of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and by relation cloſelie to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the aeternall ioy appoynted to euerie one of the ſame couenant. <hi>Rom. 9.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:3176:29"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iſmael</hi> was borne of the bond woman, and both brothers hath a great relation to the 2. Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, the calling of ſome freelie of his mercie, and the reiecting of many other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to vpright iuſtice, which was ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by caſting <hi>Jſmael</hi> and <hi>Hagar</hi> out of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brams</hi> houſe. Reade <hi>Gal. 4.</hi> yet he became a Nation of 12. Dukedomes in the land of <hi>Chuſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iſaac</hi> had two ſonnes at one time, <hi>Iaacob</hi> &amp; <hi>Eſau,</hi> who did import and ſignifie two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: to wete, the <hi>Jewes</hi> and the <hi>Gentiles:</hi> the one was choſen by the free mercie of God, the other left to condemnation, that the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of God might ſtand. <hi>Rom. 9.11.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Of <hi>Iaacob </hi>which is called <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Reade <hi>Matth. 1. Luk. 1.2.4. Joh. 1.4. Rom. 9.11. 1 Cor. 10, 11. Gall. 6. Act. 2.13.21.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The other Fathers are not recited in the newe Teſtament, nor in the olde, but onlie to prooue the line of Chriſt whole from <hi>Noah</hi> to <hi>Abram,</hi> of whom he ſhould come according to the fleſh.</p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:3176:30"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>The 3. promiſe concerning Chriſt.</label> 
                  </p>
                  <p>IN the 10. Age from <hi>Sem, Abram</hi> liued, to whom GOD ſaid, <hi>Jn thy ſeede ſhall all the Nations of the earth be bleſſed.</hi> Gen. 12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sem</hi> liued 150. yeares in <hi>Abrams</hi> time, to teach him in the right vſe of that promiſe which God had made vnto him many yeres before. <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.10 to 27.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Terah</hi> was 130. yeares when he begat <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham.</hi> 11, 32.12.4, &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 7.4. and he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vnto the 50. yeare of <hi>Jſaacs</hi> age.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abram</hi> being 110. yeares old <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.5. liued to teach <hi>Iſaac</hi> 75. yeres after. <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.7</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iſaac</hi> being 60. yeares old was borne <hi>Jaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, Gen.</hi> 25.26. <hi>Abram</hi> was then aliue and liued 15. yeares to teach <hi>Jaacob.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe ſons of <hi>Sem</hi> with their poſteritie are caſt out of the holie line, who were deadlie enemies to their kindred. <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.22, 23.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Elam</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell rows="4">their iſſue and poſteritie </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Elamites,</hi> or <hi>Perſians.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Aſſhur</hi> 
                           </cell>
                           <cell> 
                              <hi>Aſsirians.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Lud</hi> 
                           </cell>
                           <cell> 
                              <hi>Lidians.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Aram</hi> 
                           </cell>
                           <cell> 
                              <hi>Aramites,</hi> or <hi>Sirians.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:3176:30"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IAphet</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Noah,</hi> and his ſonnes: of theſe were the Iles of the Gentiles, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man after his tongue, and familie. <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis 10.2, 5.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Gomer</hi> 
                           </cell>
                           <cell rows="3">their iſſue or poſteritie. </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Tartarians.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Magog</hi> 
                           </cell>
                           <cell> 
                              <hi>Turkes, Scythians.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Madai</hi> 
                           </cell>
                           <cell> 
                              <hi>Medes.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Iauan</hi> 
                           </cell>
                           <cell rows="4">their iſſue &amp; poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, read <hi>Ezech. 38</hi> 1, 2, <hi>3, etc. 39.1, 2,</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi> People of</hi> Aſia <hi>and</hi> Graecia.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Tuball</hi> 
                           </cell>
                           <cell rows="3"> 
                              <hi>Read</hi> Ezech. 27.12, 13.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Meſech</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Tiras</hi> 
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CHam</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Noah,</hi> and his Sonnes. <hi>Geneſis</hi> 10.6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <pb n="46" facs="tcp:3176:31"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Chuſh</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell rows="4"> their iſſue &amp; poſteritie.</cell>
                           <cell> Nimrod <hi>a mightie hunter, the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of</hi> Babel. <hi>Gen. 10.8.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Miſraim</hi> 
                           </cell>
                           <cell> Egyptians <hi>in He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue</hi> Miſraims.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Pút</hi> 
                           </cell>
                           <cell> 
                              <hi>Blacke Moores.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Canaan</hi> 
                           </cell>
                           <cell> Canaanites, Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zites <hi>&amp; ſo foorth, as Gen. 10.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here may you ſee the great wiſedome of GOD, by ruling the hearts and tongues of theſe Fathers to giue their Children ſuch names, as might in it teach a true forme and proportion of his Church, as hee did by the other 10. Fathers before the floud: which being laid &amp; chained equally together, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vp a ſhort accompt of Faith and ſumme of Religion. It ſheweth to all the world the prouidence of God, and it enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth men of good conſcience, to giue their children ſignificatiue names, for imitation and examples ſake.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:3176:31"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Noah</hi> hauing found fauour with GOD, aboue manie thouſand generations, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing by a ſpirite of Prophecie, that his ſonne <hi>Sem,</hi> the eldeſt in accompt, ſhould be bleſſed, &amp; of great fame with God &amp; men, he named him <hi>Renowmed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sem</hi> perceiuing the purpoſe of his father to be fallen true in him, and knowing that perfect Renowme ſtandeth in the Sauing health of the ſoule, to make his faith know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, he named his ſonne <hi>Healing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Arphaxad</hi> being thus named, to ſhewe his Religion, that health and ſaluation ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth by the perſwading of Gods iuſtice in Chriſt, he called his ſonne, <hi>Peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sale</hi> beeing well aſſured that hee was at perfect peace with GOD, as all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full were, and yet ſeeing their trouble and miſerie in this world, hee called his Sonne <hi>Pilgrime.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Heber</hi> hauing many ſingular prerogatiues in himſelf, &amp; foreſeing <hi>diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> of the people
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3176:32"/> for their pride in building <hi>Babel,</hi> he named his ſonne <hi>Deuiding.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Peleg</hi> perceiuing that immediately vpon diuiſion and diſſolution, comes a ſtarting from the lawes of GOD, and a cutting or diſmembring from the Church, hee named his ſonne <hi>Breaking.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Regu</hi> declareth his owne ſtaye and ſound continuaunce in the Couenant, though the wicked breake and are broken off as rotten braunches: he calleth his ſonne <hi>Palme Tree.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sarug</hi> was ſpringing and ſprouting, hee was proſperous and goodly as a <hi>Palme tree</hi> among the trees of the Forreſt: &amp; although nothing could diminiſh the force of his faith, yet he called his ſonne <hi>Drie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nahor</hi> beeing eaſilie mooued with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure and anger, and drie in reſpect of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie good fruite without the Lord, hee ſawe that the ſonne of ſuch a father was to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Wretch.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Terah</hi> although indeed a poore miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wretch, and ſubiect to corruption, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3176:32"/> of ſinne in himſelfe, yet by grace ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, as by teſtimonie of his Sonnes name did import, whome hee named a <hi>high Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To euerie one of theſe may be called to mind all places of Scripture of like ſenſe, and ſo make vſe thereof: as </hi>Renowmed, Peace, Deuiding, Breaking, Palme trees<hi> for Constancie, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The yeares how long theſe Fathers liued ſerueth to great purpoſe, otherwiſe the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt had not made accompt thereof ſo plaine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore marke well the ſame, and the profite will be yours greatly.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="period">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:3176:33"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Period.</head>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument or ſumme of this Period.</head>
                  <p>REad <hi>Gen.</hi> 29, 30. there you ſhall ſee a Church in the number of 12. of the ſeede of <hi>Abram,</hi> who are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in ſcripture by diuers names, as <hi>Vine, Garden, Vineyard, a Royall nation, a peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar people, Kings and Priests, &amp;c.</hi> The Maieſtie of God did keepe them as the Apple of his eye, he wrote them vpon the Palme of his hands, he ſet them as a Signet on his finger, and he wrote their names in the booke of life.</p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:3176:33"/>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell role="label">
                              <hi>Patriarchs.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="label">Significations.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1 Ruben</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>The L. looked vpon my tribulation, my husband wil loue me.</hi> Ge. 29.32</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>2 Simeon</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>The Lord heard that J was hated. 33.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>3 Leui</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Mine huſband will loue mee and keepe me companie. 34.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>4 Iudah</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Praiſe the Lord. 25.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>5 Dan</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>God gaue ſentence on my ſide Gen. 30.6.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>6 Nepthali</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Excellent wrestling, J got the vpper hand. 8.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>7 Gad</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>A companie commeth. 11.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>8 Aſher</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Bleſſed am J, for the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters will loue me. 13.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>9 Iſachar</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>GOD hath giuen me my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. 18.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>10 Zabulon</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>GOD hath endowed me with a good dowrie. 20.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>11 Ioſeph</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>GOD hath taken away my rebuke. 23, 24.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>12 Beniamin</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>The ſonne of my ſorow. 35, 18.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:3176:34"/>
                  <p>When you miſſe them by theyr names, you ſhall knowe them by theyr ſignifications, as you read.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Read Gen.</hi> 49, there their Father <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> at his death gaue them ſeueral bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings aunſwerable to their names, and withall a Prophecie in another ſort, what ſhould come vnto them in the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dayes, by giuing them theſe <hi>Armes</hi> and <hi>Cognizances</hi> according to their Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and Tribes, wherby you may know them. And the cauſe why he ſo bleſſed them is laid downe directly: which I pray you for your owne profit to read, and marke the Storie well.</p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:3176:34"/>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell role="label">
                              <hi>Patriarchs.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="label">Armes.</cell>
                           <cell role="label">Chapters.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1 Ruben</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>water.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Gen. 49.4.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>2 Simeon</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>a Sword.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Gen. 49.5.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>3 Leui</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>a Booke.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Gen. 49.5.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>4 Iudah</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>a Lyon.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>8, 9, 10, 11, 12.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>5 Dan</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>an Adder.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Ge. 49.16, 17.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>6 Nepthali</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>a Hinde.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Gen. 49.21.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>7 Gad</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>a Banner.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Gen. 49.19.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>8 Aſher</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Bread.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Gen. 49.20.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>9 Iſachar</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>an Aſſe.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Gen. 13.14.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>10 Zabulon</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>a Shippe.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Gen. 13.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>11 Ioſeph</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>a fruitful bough</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Gen. 49.22.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>12 Beniamin</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>a Woolfe.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Gen. 49.27.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:3176:35"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Manie times you ſhall reade of theſe Tribes not by their names, nor by their ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but by their Armes, which you muſt marke, for thereby you ſhall knowe them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Reade all <hi>Deut. 33.</hi> where <hi>Moſes</hi> that kinglie Prophet at his death bleſſeth alſo the ſame 12. <hi>Tribes,</hi> ratifying alſo their former bleſsings, and enlarging the ſame by manie regall notes, whereby you may alſo knowe them, where they are diſperſed in the Bible, in what ſort they liued, and where they died.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Here you haue the number of <hi>12.</hi> wherein manie excellent things were done, which you are carefully to marke, by comparing them as you reade, particularlie. Firſt the number: </hi>As</p>
                  <p>In the <hi>Creation</hi> GOD was mindfull of theſe 12. <hi>Tribes</hi> before they were: for as they went to <hi>Canaan</hi> he brought them to <hi>Elim,</hi> where was 12. <hi>Fountaines.</hi> He deuided the yeare into 12. <hi>Moneths.</hi> He cauſed them to take 12. <hi>ſtones out of Iordan.</hi> There were
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3176:35"/> 12 <hi>ſtones</hi> in <hi>Aarons</hi> breaſt. 12. <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> Thus of all the reſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Now mark a briefe reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall</hi> of euerie Tribe, by the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation <hi>whereof, you ſhall by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon</hi> direct your memorie to manie other ſuch like.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ben</hi> loſt his prerogatiue, becauſe hee went vp to his fathers bed, therefore he was as light as water. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To this you may applie all places of fleſhlie affections or light behauiour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Simeon Leui.</label> THeir wrath was fierce againſt <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> but <hi>Leui</hi> afterward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented and ſhewed tender affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to <hi>Ioſeph:</hi> he deſtroyed I do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, therefore he had a bleſsing in <hi>Moſes</hi> will. <hi>Simeon</hi> was ſtill cruell, therefore when he came to <hi>Aegypt</hi> he was put in priſon. Alſo his ſinne with the <hi>Suhamites</hi> was great, and ſeeing he neuer repented, he was iuſtlie cut off. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.5, 6, 7.</p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:3176:36"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IVdah</hi> hath a prerogatiue that his brethren ſhould praiſe the Lord, yet who looſer tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he, who lay with his daughter <hi>Thamar:</hi> wherein are manifeſt the gifts of grace, and not of nature: for if <hi>Iudah</hi> had been rare of godlines, then the prerogatiue of nature might ſerue to cauſe Chriſt to come of him. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.8, 9, 10, 11, 12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To this you may bring all places of praiſing God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>DAn</hi> when the <hi>Tribes</hi> are ſealed <hi>Reuel.</hi> 7. is left out, wherby it is thought that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt ſhould come of him: he cauſed the firſt Idolatrie, and in this Tribe it continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vntill the remouing of the Arke from <hi>Shiloh. Gen.</hi> 49 17, 18.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To this you may referre all places that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne Superstition and Idolatrie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>NEpthali,</hi> is a Hind let go, giuing goodlie words. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.21. which thing was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with <hi>Baracke</hi> of his Tribe, and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borah</hi> of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> who ſang for the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe of <hi>Siſera,</hi> at the waters of <hi>Magedda. Iudg.</hi> 4, 6.5.</p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:3176:36"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>GAd,</hi> he ſhall leade an Hoſt of men, or a companie commeth. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.19. This was performed when <hi>Ruben, Gad</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes</hi> gaue an ouerthrow to the <hi>Hagarines. Ioſua.</hi> 1.21.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ASſer</hi> was a Farmor, he prouided bread &amp; pleaſures for a King. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.20.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ISachar</hi> was contented to liue vnder tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, like an Aſſe vnder two bindens, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than by ſeeking glorie in reſiſting euill. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.14.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ZAbulon</hi> was a Merchant, and delighted in Shippes, he dwelt neere the riuer <hi>Tharſis</hi> where was gold. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.13.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IOſeph</hi> was a goodlie man and a chaſt, he had the ſpirit of <hi>Reuel</hi> he had fauour with the maſter of the priſon. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.22.</p>
                  <p>So had <hi>Daniel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:3176:37"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ioſeph</hi> his name was changed.</p>
                  <p>So was <hi>Daniels.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was falſelie accuſed.</p>
                  <p>So was <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thus you muſt remember more by particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, whereby you may compare. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There were ſixe <hi>Iudges</hi> of this Tribe, by which glorie, his poſteritie began to deſpiſe the Tribe of <hi>Iudah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was ſold.</p>
                  <p>So was <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BEniamin,</hi> the ſonne of my ſorow. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.27, 28. <hi>Iaacob</hi> calls him, <hi>the ſonne of my right hand. Moſes</hi> calls him, <hi>the beloued of the Lord.</hi> The Temple was built in this Tribe. In this Tribe was the firſt King, he conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued one of two, when 10. fell away. <hi>Hester</hi> came of this Tribe.</p>
                  <p>So did <hi>Paule.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All the whole Storie of the Bible from A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bram to Chriſt is contained by theſe,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3176:37"/> with their Actions good or euill, and their Religion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now marke their peregrination.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iſrael</hi> was borne in <hi>Canaan. Iſrael</hi> liued 400. yeares in <hi>Aegypt</hi> and returned into <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan;</hi> from thence they were caried captiue to <hi>Babel</hi> or <hi>Babilon,</hi> whence their father <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bram</hi> was called, where they liued 70 yeres. They were reſtored to <hi>Canaan</hi> and there died.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Adam</hi> fell in <hi>Canaan,</hi> Chriſt was promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in <hi>Canaan,</hi> Chriſt was borne in <hi>Canaan,</hi> he went into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> returned into <hi>Canaan,</hi> and there died, to deliuer <hi>Iſrael</hi> from their euerlaſting bondage.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To this you may referre the vncertaine ſtate of the Church in this world.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It ſerueth to prooue the prouidence of God, who determineth euerie mans abode, the time, the place, &amp; the cauſe of his death in his euerlaſting Counſell.</p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:3176:38"/>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <head>Enemies in their time.</head>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Iſmael </hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell rows="2">
                              <hi>Midianites. Iudg.</hi> 8.24. and their race.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Eſau</hi> 
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>The continuance of this Storie is ſure. <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.17.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt ſhined in <hi>Aegypt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iaacob</hi> liued 17. yeares in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his people concerning Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Job</hi> liued in <hi>Aegypt. Gen.</hi> 47.28. By faith he ſawe Chriſt a farre off, which made him to offer. <hi>Job.</hi> 1.5. and to teach his ſonnes the ſame.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="period">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:3176:38"/>
               <head>4. PERIOD.</head>
               <p>REade <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. the going of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Aegypt</hi> towards <hi>Canaan:</hi> in which iourney you ſhall direct your memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to all that was done in 40. yeares. They pitched their Tents in 42. places, whereof ſome were pleaſant, and ſome vnpleaſant: ſo is our iourney to that heauenlie houſe whoſe builder and maker is God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here I haue laid downe what was done in euerie ſtanding, whereby you may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ramaſes</hi> ſignifieth <hi>wormes meate:</hi> ſuch is our nature, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.37, &amp;c. 13.18, 19. Mark the Paſſeouer which was eaten there. Reade <hi>Luk.</hi> 14. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.13.21. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 19.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Compare it with the Lords ſupper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Succoth</hi> ſignifieth <hi>poore Cottages:</hi> ſo are our habitations. God directeth all mens go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.21, 22. Read <hi>Haeb.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. to an heauenlie houſe. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:3176:39"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Etham</hi> ſignifieth <hi>hard ground:</hi> ſo are our worldlie commodities. <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.20.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Maarah</hi> ſignifieth <hi>Bitternes:</hi> ſo after a little comfort wee fall into trialls againe, ſhewing vs that the grace of worldlie things laſteth not. <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.23, &amp;c. All the waters were bitter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elim</hi> ſignifieth <hi>ſtrong harts:</hi> ſo God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageth the wearied and weake. There were 12. <hi>Fountaines,</hi> and 70. <hi>Palme Trees,</hi> putting them in minde of the 70 that came out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and of the 12. Tribes. <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.27, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Syn</hi> ſignifieth <hi>Thornie:</hi> thereby GOD taught them and vs that the cares and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this life, are hinderances to life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.1, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rephidim</hi> ſignifieth <hi>Temptation:</hi> there there was no water, there GOD prooued them. <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>Reade <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.5.15. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.7. <hi>1. Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>1. Timo.</hi> 6. <hi>Phile.</hi> 2. <hi>Iam.</hi> 1. <hi>2. Peter 2. Reuel. 3.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:3176:39"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sinai,</hi> ſignifieth <hi>Euerlasting temptation,</hi> there the Lawe was giuen 430. yeares after the promiſe made to <hi>Abraham. Exod.</hi> 19. <hi>Numb.</hi> 33.</p>
               <p>Reade <hi>Matth. 22.23. Luk. 2.16. Joh. 1.7.18, 19. Rom. 2.3.4.6.7.8.13. 1. Corin. 15.6. Ephe. 2. 1. Timo. 1. Haebr. 7.9, 10. Iam. 24.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which Law was deuided into</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1. <hi>Morall</hi> 
                        </cell>
                        <cell>not remoued</cell>
                        <cell rows="3"> by </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Time.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2. <hi>Judiciall</hi> 
                        </cell>
                        <cell>altered </cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Place.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3. <hi>Ceremoniall</hi> 
                        </cell>
                        <cell>abrogated </cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Perſon.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>In reading of the Law conſider wel theſe three aforeſaid: marke well the difference betwixt them.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:3176:40"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Times prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall, the feasts of</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>Sabaoths. <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.23, 24, <hi>to</hi> 30. <hi>Leuitic.</hi> 23.3, 7, 8. Saba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oths of weekes. <hi>Deut.</hi> 16.9, <hi>to</hi> 12.</item>
                        <item>Paſſeouer. <hi>Exo.</hi> 12. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 23.5, 6. <hi>Deuter.</hi> 16.1, 2, <hi>to</hi> 8.2. <hi>King.</hi> 23.21, 22, 23.</item>
                        <item>Tabernacles. <hi>Leu.</hi> 23.34, &amp;c. <hi>to</hi> 43. <hi>Deu.</hi> 16.13, 14, 15, 16 <hi>Haeb.</hi> 9.2.</item>
                        <item>Iubile yeares. <hi>Leuitic.</hi> 25.8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Places prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>Temple. 1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 6. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.16. <hi>to</hi> 25. 1. <hi>Cro.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 41.</item>
                        <item>Court. <hi>Exod.</hi> 27.9, 10, <hi>to</hi> 18.40.8, &amp;c. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 7.12.</item>
                        <item>Altar. <hi>Num.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Deut.</hi> 16.21, 22. 1. <hi>Cron.</hi> 6, 49. 2. <hi>Cron.</hi> 4.19.</item>
                        <item>Tabernacle. <hi>Exod.</hi> 26.1, 2, <hi>to</hi> 37.33.7, 8, <hi>to</hi> 23, 40. <hi>Num.</hi> 7.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>Joſ.</hi> 18.1. 1. <hi>Sa.</hi> 22.</item>
                        <item>Arke. <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.1, 2, 3, to 40. <hi>Nu.</hi> 4.1, 2, <hi>to</hi> 15.6, &amp;c. 1 <hi>ki.</hi> 8.1, 2, <hi>to</hi> 7. <hi>Nu.</hi> 10.33, <hi>to</hi> 36.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3176:40"/> 
                           <hi>Joſ.</hi> 3.6, <hi>to</hi> 17. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.6, 7.</item>
                        <item>Holy of holieſt. <hi>Exod.</hi> 26.33, 34, <hi>to</hi> 37. <hi>Num.</hi> 4,4. 1. <hi>kin.</hi> 6.19, <hi>to</hi> 36. <hi>Haeb.</hi> 9, 3.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Perſons principall.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>Aarons apparell. <hi>Exo.</hi> 28.</item>
                        <item>Leuits office. <hi>Joſ.</hi> 3, 3. <hi>Num.</hi> 3 7, <hi>to</hi> 11.4.2, 20. 1. <hi>Cro.</hi> 15. <hi>to</hi> 20. 2. <hi>Cro.</hi> 7.6. Their habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 21.1, 2, &amp;c.</item>
                        <item>Creatures for ſacrifices. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 2.2, 3, &amp;c. 3, 4, 6, 7, 11.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>THeſe particulars beeing well and adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly conſidered by Bookes and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as is laid downe, will greatly open vnto you the chiefeſt effects and purpoſes of the lawe. Withall, you ſhalbe thereby called to minde of other ſuch like places els where, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie of which particulars being ſpiritually applied, &amp; interpreted by the Goſpel, muſt of neceſsitie eſtabliſh and confirme a weak and a troubled ſoule.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Christ was knowen and preached in the Lawe.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:3176:41"/>
               <p>The Lambe eaten <hi>Exo.</hi> 12. figured Chriſt moſt plainlie, which was promiſed to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> the ſelfe ſame day 430 yeres before. <hi>Exo. 12. Gal. 3.17, 18.</hi> In which day the <hi>Jewes</hi> retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from <hi>Babel.</hi> In which day Chriſt was killed, the which <hi>Moſes</hi> knewe verie well: therefore he ſaid, <hi>This day ſhall be vnto you a remembrance, &amp;c. Exod. 12.14.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Manna, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.15. The water out of the ſtone 17.6. ſignified Chriſt. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.3. Their offerings pointed to Chriſt. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 16 <hi>Numb.</hi> 19. <hi>Haeb.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>The Braſen Serpent <hi>Numb.</hi> 21.6, to 10. ſignified Chriſt. <hi>Iob.</hi> 3.14, 15. <hi>Aaron</hi> the hie Prieſt <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.29. Chriſt <hi>Haebr.</hi> 4.14. In <hi>Mount Sinai</hi> by plaine lawes, ſaying: I am the Lord thy God, which pointed to Chriſt, for God the Father in iuſtice was to them as a conſuming fire. Againe, I will ſend an Angell before thee. <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.20. The Angell of the Couenant ſaith <hi>Malach.</hi> 3.1. S. <hi>Paule</hi> pointing to this time &amp; to this people ſaid, As the Goſpell was preached vnto vs, euen ſo was it vnto them. <hi>Haeb. 4.2.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iotbatha</hi> ſignifieth a <hi>Turning away.</hi> There
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:3176:41"/> 
                  <hi>Chorah, Dathan, &amp;c.</hi> rebelled. <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.1, 2, 3.33.34.</p>
               <p>Reade <hi>Act.</hi> 7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.13. 2. <hi>Timo.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Iam.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hor</hi> ſignifieth <hi>Declaring,</hi> or <hi>ſhewing,</hi> a Mount where <hi>Aaron</hi> died 14. yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he came from <hi>Aegypt. Numb.</hi> 20, 22.33.37. ſhewing the death of that perpetual <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> and high Prieſt Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zalmonah</hi> ſignifieth the <hi>Shadow of a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> there they loathed Manna, &amp;c. <hi>Numb.</hi> 21.1.5. There they were ſtinged. 6. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Read <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moah</hi> ſignifieth of <hi>the Father,</hi> who was <hi>Lots</hi> ſonne of his eldeſt daughter, of whome came the wicked <hi>Moabites Iſrael</hi> falling to Idolatrie are ouercome by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſo brought into ſubiection: there they commit whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome with the daughters of <hi>Madian:</hi> there <hi>Balaac</hi> hired <hi>Balaam,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Numb.</hi> 27.10, 11. &amp;c. 33.44.</p>
               <p>Read <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6.10. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 1. <hi>Theſ</hi> 4. <hi>Reu.</hi> 2.14.17, 18. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The reſt of the ſtandings ſeeme to no ſuch purpoſe, as theſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="period">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:3176:42"/>
               <head>5. Period.</head>
               <p>Wherein conſider a
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Conquerour.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Land conquered.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>IOſua</hi> the <hi>Conquerour</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Moſes,</hi> he was one of the twelue that viewed the Land, and one of the two that beleeued. He was 67 yeares when he began, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued 17 yeares. <hi>Moſes</hi> called him <hi>Theſus,</hi> becauſe he was to be a figure of <hi>Christ Jhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi> In him all the promiſes to <hi>Abram</hi> and to others concerning <hi>Canaan,</hi> was fulfilled. <hi>Moſes</hi> by the Lawe ſhewed them that good Land, but <hi>Ioſhua</hi> brought them into it: to ſhewe foreuer, that the Lawe bringeth no man to heauen, but <hi>Iheſus Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Land conquered,</hi> it was exceeding fruitfull, pointing to the land of the liuing. Strong people as <hi>Giants.</hi> 324. great Cities. 31. Kings: a proportion of Sathans force, of the Captiuitie in <hi>Aegipt</hi> and in <hi>Babylon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Canaan</hi> was a place that lacked nothing
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:3176:42"/> which was in the world. <hi>Jud.</hi> 18.10. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare it with the kingdome of heauen.</p>
               <p>It was ſeauen yeares in conquering, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the words of <hi>Chaleb,</hi> ſaying <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeares olde was I, when Moſes the ſeruaunt of the Lord ſent me from Kadeſbarnea to espie the Land, &amp;c. Ioſua.</hi> 14, 7. Looke <hi>Num.</hi> 13.27.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſpace that we came from Kadeſbarnea was 38. yeares, &amp;c.</hi> Deut. 2.14, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Adde 7. to 40. and to 38. that makes vp 85. <hi>Calebs</hi> age. <hi>Ioſua</hi> 14.10.</p>
               <p>Heere is a compariſon, as the Land was in conquering 6. yeares, and at reſt the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth: ſo God in ſixe daies wrought, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth the ſeauenth. This is the ſtate of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and the courſe of their life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="period">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:3176:43"/>
               <head>6. Period.</head>
               <p>HEere you ſhall haue in the booke of Iudges by ſucceſsion thirteene Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours, who were ſtirred vp to be deliuerers of the poore oppreſſed people of God. They were men of great faithfulnes and courage, as the Storie dooth witneſſe. The ſinnes of the people were ſuch and ſo grieuous, as God did greatly puniſh by men that were twice worſe than themſelues. This Storie of the Iudges, ſerueth verie well to ſhewe the iudgement of God againſt obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſinners, and his mercies to the penitent. If you marke the Storie well, you ſhall find it full of waightie matters: and by manie particulars therein, you ſhalbe called to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member other places of like ſenſe and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</p>
               <p>Here I haue diſtinguiſhed the Iudges fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Oppreſſours, the time how long the one and the other raigned: whence the Iudges were, and who the oppreſſors were: as is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in their ſeuerall Stories: in which you muſt be perfect.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:3176:43"/>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Oppreſſor.THe <hi>Philistines,</hi> the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> the <hi>Sido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> the <hi>Heuites,</hi> and <hi>Chuſan</hi> of Meſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potamia. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8. Vnder whom they ſerued. 8. yeares.</item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. Iudge.<hi>OThoniel</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Jſrael,</hi> and ſet them at reſt fortie yeares. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 3.9, 10, 11.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Oppreſſor.<hi>EGlon</hi> the King of <hi>Moab</hi> was ſtirred vp againſt them, whome they ſerued 18. yeares, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 3.12, 13, 14, 15, 16.</item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>2. Iudge.<hi>EHud</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Beniamin,</hi> deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them, and they had peace foure ſcore yeares Iudg. 3.17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, &amp;c.</item>
                        <pb n="72" facs="tcp:3176:44"/>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. Oppreſſor.<hi>IAbin</hi> King of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and <hi>Siſera</hi> his Captaine. Hee had nine hundred Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots of yron. Hee vexed <hi>Jſrael</hi> 20. yeares. Iudg. 4.1, 2, 3, 4.</item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>3. Iudg.<hi>DEborah</hi> a Propheteſſe raigned with <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racke</hi> of the tribe of <hi>Nepthali,</hi> ſhee being of the tribe of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> deſtroyed the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of <hi>Siſera,</hi> &amp; <hi>Siſera</hi> himſelf was ſlain by a a woman And <hi>Iabin</hi> the King was alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed. The Land had reſt fortie yeares. Iudg 4.4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, &amp;c. 5.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, &amp;c.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. Oppreſſor.THe <hi>Madianites</hi> preuailed againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and vexed them grieuouſly ſeauen yeres. The <hi>Amalakites</hi> and they of the Eaſt: <hi>Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> 6.1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>2, 3, 4, 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>6. Their chiefe Princes were <hi>Oreb</hi> and <hi>Zeb</hi> 7, 25. <hi>Zeba</hi> and <hi>Zalmonah</hi> Kings of <hi>Madian</hi> 8, 5.</item>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:3176:44"/>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>4. Iudge.<hi>GEdeon</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> was eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially called by an Angell from the thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of wheate, to threſh and beate the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Gods people: whoſe authoritie was miraculouſly confirmed. With a few he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed manie in number as the graſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. The Countrey was in quietneſſe in his dayes full fortie yeares. He was called <hi>Ierub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baal.</hi> Iudg. 6.11, 12, 13, &amp;c. 7.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, &amp;c. 8.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, &amp;c. 32.</item>
                        <item>5. Iudge.<hi>ABimelech</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Ephraim.</hi> He ſlew his brethren: for the which he was ſlaine himſelfe by a woman with a ſtone, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had raigned 3. yeares. Iudg. 8.33, 34, 35.9.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, &amp;c.</item>
                        <item>6. Iudge.<hi>TOla</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Jſachar,</hi> hee iudged <hi>Iſrael</hi> twentie and three yeares. Iudges 10.1, 2.</item>
                        <pb n="74" facs="tcp:3176:45"/>
                        <item>7. Iudge.<hi>IAir</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> a <hi>Gileadite,</hi> ruled Iſrael twentie two yeares. Iudges 10.3, 4, 5.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. Oppreſſor.THe <hi>Philistins</hi> and the <hi>Ammonites</hi> vexed and oppreſſed Iſrael 18. yeares. Iudges 10.6, 7, 8, 9.</item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>8. Iudge.<hi>IEpthe</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> deliuered Iſrael, and ruled them in peace 6. yeares. Iudg. 11.1, 2, 3, &amp;c. 12.1, 2, &amp;c.</item>
                        <item>9. Iudge.<hi>ABeſan</hi> of <hi>Iudah</hi> deliuered them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their enemies, and kept the Land in quietnes ſeauen yeares. Iudg. 12.8, 9, 10.</item>
                        <pb n="75" facs="tcp:3176:45"/>
                        <item>10. <hi>Iudge.</hi>
                           <hi>EGlon</hi> of the tribe of <hi>Zabulon</hi> iudged <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> 10. yeares. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 12.11, 12.</item>
                        <item>11. <hi>Iudge.</hi>
                           <hi>ABden</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> ruled <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> in peace eight yeares. <hi>Iudges</hi> 12.13, 14, 15.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. Oppreſſor.THE <hi>Philistines</hi> vexed them ſore fortie yeares. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 13, 1.</item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>12. <hi>Iudge.</hi>
                           <hi>SAmpſon</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Dan</hi> was made their King or Captaine after a ſtrange and moſt miraculous ſort, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed moſt triumphantly iudging <hi>Iſrael</hi> twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeares. <hi>Iudges</hi> 13.3, 4, 5, 6. &amp;c. 14.1, 2, 3, 4, &amp;c. 15.1, 2, 3, 4. &amp;c. 16.1, 2, 3, 4, &amp;c.</item>
                        <pb n="76" facs="tcp:3176:46"/>
                        <item>13. Iudge.<hi>HEli</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Leui,</hi> deliuered <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> and preſerued them in peace 40. yeares 1. Sam. 1, 2, 3, 4.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The Iudges continued in Storic moſt ſure and certaine 450. yeares, reckoning withall the yeares of the Oppreſſors. <hi>Act.</hi> 13, 12.</p>
               <p>If you marke the particular Storie of theſe Iudges and Oppreſſors, it will not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make you perfect in this booke of Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es: but alſo by compariſon direct you to manie more bookes for matter of like qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="period">
               <head>7. Period.</head>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:3176:46"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here J will ſpeake brieflie and particularlie of the Kings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAule</hi> ſignifieth, <hi>deſired of the people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> he was of the Tribe of <hi>Beniamin,</hi> which was a great prerogatiue to that Tribe beeing the leaſt and the laſt: he was an hypocrite, and an open perſecutor. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.13, 18, 19.20</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>DAuid</hi> beleeued God, and his kingdome was reckoned when the Arke was reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to <hi>Judah</hi> at Eaſter. So Chriſt at Eaſter was proclaimed King generall: he was of the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> of the root of <hi>Ieſſe</hi> borne in <hi>Bethelem.</hi> He killed a Beare, a Lyon, and a <hi>Philistin</hi> that defied all <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Herein he is a figure of Chriſt. He had manie enemies, therein he is a figure of the Church. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16, 17. <hi>Dauid</hi> was vpright, except in one thing. <hi>1. King. 15, 5.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAlomon</hi> ſignifieth <hi>Peaceable:</hi> ſo was his kingdome: for his wiſedome and order in Religion he was a figure of Chriſt: he was
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:3176:47"/> extreamelie wicked. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 11, 4.5. Yet he was ſaued. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7, 13.14. Heerein he was a figure of the Church.</p>
               <p>He laid the foundation of the Temple in <hi>Moriah,</hi> 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 3, 1. where <hi>Adam</hi> was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, where <hi>Iſaac</hi> was offered, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 22.2. where Chriſt died, where afterwards the holie kingdome was deuided into 2. parts, <hi>1. King. 12.</hi> according to the Lords words vnto <hi>Salomon.</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 11.11, 12, 13.14, 15. But after 490. yeares expired, it was thrown together againe, as in <hi>Ezech.</hi> 37.16, 17, 18. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thus haue I diſtinguiſhed the Kings in their order as they ſucceeded, who were wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, who were godlie, and what Prophet, one, or mo was vnder euerie King, whereby the bookes of the Kings being laid with the Prophets, the one expounds the other plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and eaſilie, if you marke what ſinnes the people committed, what happened to them or to their Kings, and what not, whereof the Prophets did by particulars ſpeake of.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="list_of_kings">
                           <pb n="79" facs="tcp:3176:47"/>
                           <head>Kings of <hi>Judah.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>REhoboam</hi> ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Salomon.</hi> The Tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and the Tribe of <hi>Beniamin</hi> claue to him: thence it was called the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Iudah,</hi> his throne was at <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem:</hi> he was 14. yeares whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he began to raigne and continued 17. yeres <hi>1. Kings 12.1,</hi> to <hi>25. 21,</hi> he and his people were wicked. <hi>22.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Seſack</hi> King of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> came in the fifth yeare of his raigne and ſpoyled <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and the Temple, and caried away their treaſures. <hi>1. King. 14.25, 26, 27, 28.</hi> He died 31.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Abia</hi> his ſonne raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:3176:48" rendition="simple:additions"/> 41. yeares, ye was godlie. <hi>1. King. 15.9, 10, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Aſa</hi> his ſonne raigned 41. yeares, he was god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, <hi>1. King. 15.9, 10, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Ahaziah</hi> raigned 1. yere. 2. <hi>King. 8.25, 26,</hi> wicked. <hi>27. Iehu</hi> ſlewe him 9, 27. he is alſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Ochoſias his mother <hi>Athalia</hi> the daughter of <hi>Omri</hi> king of <hi>Iſrael</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Eliſha</hi> propheſied, <hi>2. Kings 8, 24. &amp;c. 9. &amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Athalia</hi> his mother raigned ſixe yeares, ſhe ſlewe all the Kings ſons ſauing <hi>Ioaſh</hi> who was
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:3176:48"/> hid from her <hi>11, 2.</hi> ſhe her ſelfe was ſlaine. <hi>11. 3, 16.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Ioaſh</hi> when he was 7. yeares old <hi>11. 17, 18 19</hi> godlie, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he raigned <hi>40.</hi> yeres <hi>12, 1. &amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Amaſiah</hi> his Sonne raigned 29. yeres. <hi>2. K. 12, 21.14, 2.</hi> ſlaine <hi>14, 19</hi> godlie <hi>14, 3.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Ahaſiah</hi> or <hi>Vziah</hi> raigned 52. yeares <hi>14, 21</hi> godlie. <hi>15, 2. 3. 4.</hi> died, 7.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Eſai</hi> propheſied.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Hoſea, Amos.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Iothan</hi> his ſon raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:3176:49"/> 16. yeares, <hi>15, 7.</hi> godlie. <hi>34. 35. 36.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Micha, Oſea, Eſai</hi> propheſied.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Ahaz</hi> his ſonne raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned 16. yeares. <hi>2. King. 15, 38.</hi> his people wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. <hi>16, 2.3.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Nahum, Eſai, OſeaEzec. Micha.</hi> prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Hezekiah</hi> his ſonne raigned 29. yeres, <hi>2. K. 16, 20.28, 2.</hi> died <hi>20, 21.</hi> godlie.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Eſai, Oſea, Micha,</hi> propheſied.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Senacherib</hi> came vp againſt <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi>
                              <pb n="83" facs="tcp:3176:49"/> &amp; tooke them <hi>18, 13.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Eſai</hi> propheſied. <hi>19, 2</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Manaſſes, Hezekiah</hi> his ſonne raigned 55. yeares, he began at <hi>12.</hi> wicked. <hi>1. King. 21.</hi> he repented. <hi>2. Chro. 33.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Jn the 3 yeare of his raigne <hi>Eſai</hi> was Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Abacuck</hi> in the 36. yeare of his raigne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Ammon</hi> his ſonne at 22. yeres began, and raigned two yeres wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. <hi>2. King. 21, 19. &amp;c</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Ioſiah</hi> his ſonne at 8.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:3176:50"/> yeares olde began, and raigned 31 yeares god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. <hi>22, 23.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Pharo Necho</hi> king of <hi>Aegypt</hi> ſlew him. 29.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Zephania</hi> prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Ieremie</hi> began in the thirteene yeare of his raigne.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Zephaniah</hi> in the 20 yeare, <hi>Abdias</hi> in the 26 yeare.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Iehoaz</hi> his ſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan at 23. yeare, and raigned three moneths wicked.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Pharo Necho</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned him, &amp; ſet the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:3176:50"/> land to tribute. <hi>2. King 23, 31. &amp;c.</hi> He placed</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Eliakim</hi> in his ſtead, and changed his name into <hi>Iehoiakim,</hi> he was 11. yeares vnder taxes to the King of <hi>Aegypt</hi> wicked, after that the time of their captiuitie came, ſpoken of <hi>20, 17.</hi> 23, 27. at <hi>Babel.</hi> There <hi>Ieremie, Ezech. Dan.</hi> propheſied. <hi>Eſai.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>King of <hi>Babel</hi> made <hi>Mattamiah</hi> his vncle king in his ſteade, and changed his name <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dechia,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was 21 yeares olde, he raigned
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:3176:51"/> eleuen yeares wicked: he rebelled againſt the King of <hi>Babel:</hi> in the 9. yere of his raigne the Citie was beſieged, he pulled out his eyes, bound him in chaines, and burnt vp the citie. <hi>2. King. 24, 25.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Ieremie</hi> his prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie is accompliſhed. 25, 11.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Ezech. Dan. Hagg.</hi> propheſied.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="list_of_kings">
                           <pb n="79" facs="tcp:3176:47"/>
                           <head>Kings of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>IEroboam</hi> was the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther K. ten Tribes held with him, thence it was called the king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whoſe ſeate was at <hi>Samaria,</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 12.12, 13, 16. he &amp; his people were wicked. 1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 12.26, 27, 28, 29, &amp;c. Hee raigned 20. yeares. Here is a proportion of the Church of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt. ten againſt 2:</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Nadab</hi> his Sonne raigned two yeares. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 14.20. he was wicked 15.25.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Achab</hi> his Son raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned wicked. <hi>Ieſabell</hi> his wife 1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 16.28, &amp;c. <hi>Eliah</hi> propheſied. 1. <hi>K.</hi> 17.18.19.20.21</p>
                           <pb n="80" facs="tcp:3176:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Micha</hi> propheſied, 1. <hi>King.</hi> 22.9, 14, 15.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Achab</hi> ſlaine 34, 35.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Ahaziah</hi> raigned two yeres. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 22. 41, 51. wickedlie. 52. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3. died. 17.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Eliah</hi> propheſied. 3, 4.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Jehoram</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Achab</hi> raigned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had no ſonne 2. <hi>King.</hi> 1, 17.12, yeres 3, 1.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Eliah</hi> is taken vp 2, 1. &amp;c. and 3. yeare of his raigne.</p>
                           <pb n="81" facs="tcp:3176:48"/>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Eliſha</hi> propheſied. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 3, 14. Kings of <hi>Aram</hi> beſiegeth <hi>Samariah.</hi> 6, 24. hee was hurt and died 9, 24.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Iehu</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Iehoſophat</hi> is annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted King by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eliſha.</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 9, 1. &amp;c he ſlaieth <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the word of the Lord. 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 21, 13. and <hi>Ahaziah</hi> king of <hi>Iudah,</hi> 2. <hi>K.</hi> 9, 27. he ſlew <hi>Iezabel</hi> &amp; all <hi>Achabs</hi> brood 10. &amp;c. godlie: He died hauing raigned 25. yeares 36.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Iehoahaz</hi> his ſonne raigned 17. yeares,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:3176:49"/> 13, 1. wicked, and ſo died. 2. 9.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Iehoaſh</hi> his ſon raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned 16. yeares 13, 10. wicked. 11.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Eliſha</hi> died the third yere of his raigne 13, 20.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> is ranſac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:3176:49"/> the ſecond time: the ſame <hi>Iehoaſh</hi> took <hi>Amaſiah</hi> King of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> brake the walls, carried awaye their treaſures, died. 2. <hi>Kin.</hi> 14, 13. &amp;c.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Ionah</hi> propheſied.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Jeroboam</hi> his ſonne raigned 41. yeres, 14, 23. wicked, 24. died. 29.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Ionas, Amos</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Zachariah</hi> his ſonne raigned ſixe moneths 8, 15. wicked. 9.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Ionah</hi> propheſied.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Shallum</hi> the Sonne
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:3176:50"/> of <hi>Iabeſh</hi> conſpired a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, he raigned a moneth. 15.10, 11, &amp;c.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Mehanaen</hi> killed him, and raigned ten yeares wicked. 15. 14, 15, &amp;c.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Pekahiah</hi> his ſonne raigned two yeares wicked. 15, 23. 24.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Pekah</hi> his captaine raigned twentie yeres wicked. 15. 25, 27.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſlew him, &amp; raigned 9. yeares 15, 30. 17, 1. wicked.</p>
                           <pb n="85" facs="tcp:3176:50"/>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Salmanaſer</hi> king of <hi>Aſſurd</hi> beſieged <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria</hi> three yeares, &amp; ſubdued them &amp; the King. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 17. &amp;c. 18.9, 10, 11.</p>
                           <pb n="86" facs="tcp:3176:51"/>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="period">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:3176:51"/>
               <head>8. Period.</head>
               <p>HEre all the world may ſee the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightnes of Gods iuſtice in the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of ſinne, euen in his owne deare people, by giuing them ouer into the hands of ſuch cruel Kings as would not ſpare them whiles they were vnder their gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And here is ſet foorth verie clearelie the riches of his grace, and the vnſpeakable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his mercies, in ſtirring and raiſing the hearts of thoſe beaſtlie and vnnaturall kings to lenitie, to fauour, and to liberalitie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, (as he did to the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> to lend them coſtlie veſſells and rich iewells) whom they had before moſt bitterlie ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacked and vnnaturallie robbed. Heere you ſhall ſee a true proportion of the Church of Antichriſt, whoſe earthlie glorie reached vnto the heauens, and whoſe dominions mounted ouer all: yet their ende is with a flood or with fire, deſtruction irrecouera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And who ſeeth not in this booke the wonderfull prouidence of GOD, and the worke of his aeternall ſpirit in <hi>Daniel,</hi> recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding moſt exactlie all that was done and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:3176:52"/> ſpoken during their 70. yeres captiuitie, and whatſoeuer elſe was to be performed thence foorth to Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In this Booke of <hi>Daniel</hi> are two ſpeciall things to be marked.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The one, what Kings ruled in the ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeares.</p>
               <p>The other, what Kings ruled thence vnto Chriſt.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Three kings during the captiuitie.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Nabucadnezzar. Dan. 1, 2, 3, 4.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Euilmerodach. 2. Kin. 25, 27,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Balthaſhar. Dan. 5, 8,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nabucadnezzar</hi> ſawe in a viſion a great Image, whoſe glorie was excellent, and the forme terrible. <hi>Dan. 2, 31.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>His head of fine gold. 32.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>His breasts and armes of ſiluer. 32.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>His bellie and thighes of braſſe. 32.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:3176:52"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>His legges of yron. 33.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>His feete part of yron and part of clay. 33.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The head of Gold.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>NAbucadnezzar</hi> a King of Kings, to whom GOD gaue power, ſtrength and glorie. <hi>Daniel</hi> 2.37, 38. For his greatnes he is compared to a Tree, whoſe height reached to the heauens, &amp;c. <hi>Dan. 4.16, 17, 18. Dan. 7, 4.</hi> ſeeth this great King in a dreame as a Lyon, with Eagles wings pluckt off: it was lifted vp and ſet vpon his feete as a man, and a mans heart was giuen him, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying his vnnatural affections and his cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie. The other two Kings are referred in compariſon to this firſt King. Who Raigned iuſt 45. yeares, as appeareth thus. He tooke <hi>Iehoiachin</hi> King of <hi>Iudah</hi> in the 8. yeare of his raigne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Euilmerodach</hi> his ſonne who ſucceeded him, lifted vp <hi>Iehoiachin</hi> out of priſon when he had ſo laine 37. yeares.</p>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:3176:53"/>
                  <p>So you muſt put eight yeares in which <hi>Nabucadnezzer</hi> raigned, to thirtie ſeauen yeres in which <hi>Iehoiachin</hi> was raiſed vp, that makes vp iuſt 45. yeares the whole raigne of this firſt King.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Euilmerodach</hi> raigned 22. yeares.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Baltaſhar</hi> raigned 3. yeares. <hi>Dan. 8, 1.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus you ſee plainlie the 70. yeares fullie accompliſhed in the particular raigne of theſe three Kings, according to a propheſie. <hi>Ieremie 25, 12, 27, 7.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now the head of Gold is gone off and quite taken away. The Kings of <hi>Babel</hi> are extinguiſhed, and the 70. yeares expired.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="period">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:3176:53"/>
               <head>9. Period.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DAniel</hi> vnderſtanding that the ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeares in the deſolation of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> were accompliſhed, he turned his face vnto the Lord God, towards the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> and the holie Mountaine confeſsing the ſinnes of the people, &amp; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that his face might ſhine vppon his San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie, which had ſo long laine waſt and deſolate, preſcribed and foretold by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Leuit. 26, 40. &amp;c. 1. King. 8, 46, to 54.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whiles he was yet ſpeaking vnto GOD the Angell <hi>Gabriel</hi> came fleeing about the time of the euening oblation, ſaying:
<q>Seuentie weekes are determined vpon thy people and vpon thy holie Citie to bring in euerlasting righteouſnes, <hi>Dan. 9, 24.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Here is laid downe a plaine and an eaſie accompt of all the yeares from <hi>Daniels</hi> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion 9, 21. at the Edict, vnto the death of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt the Prince of Peace, which is very direct, if you marke it.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:3176:54"/>
               <p>Euerie weeke hath ſeuen daies. The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell meaneth for euerie day in the weeke a yeare, ſeuen daies ſeuen yeares, after the rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning of the <hi>Iubile</hi> yeare. <hi>Leuit. 29.8, 9, 10.</hi> The whole is 490 yeares.</p>
               <p>The ſame Angell through the merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God, for the more plainnes and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuitie, deuideth the ſame ſeuentie weekes into three parts, after this manner, in <hi>Daniel, 9, 25.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt part, from the going foorth of the commandement that the people <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhould bee freed in the firſt yeare of <hi>Darius</hi> to build and finiſh the Temple at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> ſhall bee ſeuen weekes: that is to ſay, 49. yeares.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Jewes</hi> confeſſe 46. yeares in which the Temple was a building, <hi>Ioh. 2, 20.</hi> In the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther firſt yeare they were hindred from their worke. <hi>Ezra. 4. Nehemi. 4.</hi> In which three yeares of trouble <hi>Cirus</hi> raigned, <hi>Dan. 10.1, 2.</hi> Yet according to the time prefixed it was finiſhed. <hi>Ezra 6. Nehemias 7.8.9.10.11.12.13.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:3176:54"/>
                  <head>Armes and breasts of <hi>ſiluer.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Part of the Image which <hi>Nabucadnezzar</hi> ſaw <hi>Dan.</hi> 2, 39. are 10. Kings of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> who were 130. yeares conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance after the Captiuitie, which are theſe.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cyrus,</hi> or <hi>Darius.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> or <hi>Cambiſes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Aſſuerus</hi> or <hi>Darius.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Histaspes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Zerxes.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Theſe raigned 29. yeares. In the 20. yeare of the raigne of <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> or <hi>Darius,</hi> the Temple was finiſhed being full 49. yeares where they troubled <hi>Jſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>There were other Kings that made vp the 130. yeres before mentioned after the building,</hi> which were theſe.</p>
                  <list>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:3176:55"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ochus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Artaxerxes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ochus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arſes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Darius</hi> the <hi>Perſian.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Theſe goodly Kings like armes &amp; breaſts of ſiluer, <hi>Daniel</hi> ſeeth them like a Beare with three ribbes in his mouth, which ſaid, <hi>Riſe and deuoure much fleſh.</hi> So did they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede deuoure the Saints of GOD. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel.</hi> 7, 6.</p>
                  <p>Now the armes and breaſts of ſiluer are cut off: Kings of <hi>Madai</hi> and <hi>Paras</hi> are ended.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>2.<hi> Part of</hi> Daniels <hi>diuiſion of Time. 9, 26. thus.</hi>
                     </label> 
                  </p>
                  <p>THreeſcore and two Weekes ſhall bee a troubleſome time, after the which the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:3176:55"/> Prince of peace, the King of glorie, and the Meſsiah ſhall be ſlaine: euen he ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Citie and the Sanctuarie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jn this time the people of GOD ſuffer great perſecutions.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The bellie and thighes <hi>of Braſſe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doth ſignifie King <hi>Alexanders</hi> power.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TO this belongeth the viſion of <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> 8.3, 4. A Goate Buck with ahorne, which being broken off, comes out in ſtead thereof foure heads, ſignifying <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anders</hi> foure Captains, fighting two to two: which two firſt is alſo the legges of yron &amp; claye, and their ſucceſſours: and the fourth Beaſt with tenne hornes. <hi>Alexander</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued 6. yeares.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:3176:56"/>
                  <head>His legges of Jron.</head>
                  <p>IS the Beaſt which <hi>Daniel</hi> ſawe 7, 7. verie fearefull and ſtrong with yron teeth burſt in peeces, and ſtamped the reſidue vnder his feete, who was the fourth kingdome in the earth ſubduing all to himſelfe. 23.</p>
                  <p>The ten hornes are ten Kings ſtronger than the <hi>Iewes</hi> that ſhal riſe out of <hi>Siria</hi> and <hi>Aegypt,</hi> whereof one is ſaid to bee a little horne, 8, 7, 11. boaſting and bragging a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the moſt higheſt.</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>Iron like</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1. S: Nicator.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2. A: Soter.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3. A: Theos.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4. S: Callicus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:3176:56"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5. S: Ceraunus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>6. A: Negas.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>7. S: Philop.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>8. A: Epimanes.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iauan.</hi> kings of <hi>Aegypt</hi> yron like to make vp the ten hornes.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>9. To: Lagie.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>10. To: Philodelphus.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>His feete part of yron and part <hi>of Clay.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Were <hi>(Jauan)</hi> Kings of <hi>Babel</hi> clay like, in number 12.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Kings ruled as Beaſts moſt beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and vnnaturallie, and as yron verie ſtrong and inuincible two hundred ninetie foure
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:3176:57"/> yeares to <hi>Cleopatras</hi> death, who confirmed <hi>Herode</hi> in <hi>Judah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>3. Part of <hi>Daniels</hi> deuiſion of <hi>Times.</hi>
                     </label> 
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p> Hee ſhall confirme the Couenaunt with manie for one weeke: and in the middest of the weeke hee ſhall cauſe the Sacrifice and Oblation to ceaſe. <bibl>Dan. 9, 27.</bibl>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>THeſe wordes hath plaine relation to Ieſus Chriſt his Office and death, for <hi>One weeke,</hi> as in the accompt afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſtandeth for ſeauen yeares, a yeare for a day.</p>
                  <p>In the middeſt of the ſame Weeke, that is to ſaye, in the middeſt of this laſt ſeauen yeares, Chriſt was baptized, and did preach this laſt halfe ſeauen, confirming his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie with miracles, ſignes and wonders, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the ſame three yeares, and halfe the ende of <hi>Daniels</hi> weeke was ended.</p>
                  <p>In which he ſuffred his paſsion according as it was before decreed manie thouſande
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:3176:57"/> yeares in the counſell of his Father, who te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified of him vnto all Nations ſaying, <hi>This is my welbeloued Sonne, in whome I am well pleaſed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <p>
               <hi>Now hauing generally, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly compared the olde Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the new: you ſhall in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other ſort plainly learn how to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the New Testament with the Olde.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:3176:58"/>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label" cols="2">Legall.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Ioh.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Gen.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Mat.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Exod.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Luk.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Leuit.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Mar</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Num</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label" cols="2">Hiſtoricall.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>act</hi> 1.</cell>
                     <cell rows="5">
                        <hi>Ioſua</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>act 4.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="5">
                        <hi>Iudg.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>act</hi> 10</cell>
                     <cell rows="5">
                        <hi>Ruth</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>act</hi> 14</cell>
                     <cell rows="6">
                        <p>1. <hi>Sa.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>2. <hi>Sa.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>act</hi> 15</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <p>1. <hi>K.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>2. <hi>K.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>act</hi> all</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <p>1. <hi>Cr.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>2. <hi>Cr.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>act</hi> 10</cell>
                     <cell rows="5">
                        <hi>Ezra</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>act</hi> 10</cell>
                     <cell rows="5">
                        <hi>Nehe</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>act</hi> 25</cell>
                     <cell rows="2">
                        <hi>Hest.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label" cols="2">Sapientall.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Iames.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="7">
                        <hi>Iob.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. <hi>Pet. </hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. <hi>Pet.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. <hi>Iohn</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2 <hi>Iohn</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3. <hi>Iohn</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Iude.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Haebr.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Pſalm.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Galath.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="10">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Prou.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Eccl.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Epheſ.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Philip.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Colloſſ.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. <hi>Timo.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. <hi>Timo.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Titus.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Phile.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Roman.</hi> all.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cant.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label" cols="2">Propheticall.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Reuel.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Daniel.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:3176:58"/>
            <p>The other Prophets are to bee compared with the Lawe, which is enlarged by time, by place, and by perſons, either paſt, preſent or to come, in this order, Booke and Chapter.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Propheticall.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Legall.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Eſay.</hi> 1, <hi>vnto</hi> 28.6, </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 1, 1.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>40, <hi>to</hi> 25.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 18, 4, 3.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 40, 27. <hi>to</hi> 16. <hi>of</hi> 41.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 42, 5, <hi>to</hi> 21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 1,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 27, 6. <hi>to</hi> 14. <hi>of</hi> 28.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 1, 1.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 43.22. <hi>to</hi> 23, <hi>of</hi> 44,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Leuit.</hi> 1.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 54, 1.10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 6, 8.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 49.15. <hi>to</hi> 5. <hi>of</hi> 51.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 7, 12.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 54, 11. <hi>to</hi> 22.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.26.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 51, 12. <hi>to</hi> 12. <hi>of</hi> 52, 60.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 16, 18.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 61, 16. <hi>to</hi> 10. <hi>of</hi> 63,</cell>
                     <cell>26.7.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>55, <hi>to</hi> 9. <hi>of</hi> 56,</cell>
                     <cell>29, 10.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Propheticall.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Legall.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Ierem.</hi> 1, 2, 3. <hi>to</hi> 26.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Num.</hi> 30, 2.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 7, 6. <hi>to</hi> 2, 8,</cell>
                     <cell>33, 2.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 16, 19. <hi>to</hi> 14. <hi>of</hi> 17.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Leuit.</hi> 6, 1.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 32, 6. <hi>to</hi> 28.</cell>
                     <cell>26, 3.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 34 8. <hi>to the end.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>25, 1.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 16, 13. <hi>to end.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Exo.</hi> 21, 1.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 
                        <hi>Ezech,</hi> 22, <hi>to</hi> 23, 15.</cell>
                     <cell>10, 1.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 28, 25. <hi>to</hi> 30.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Leuit.</hi> 16,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 43, 10. <hi>to the end.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Exo</hi> 6, 2.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 46, 13. <hi>to the end.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>20, 20.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 
                        <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2, 1. <hi>to</hi> 22.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Leui.</hi> 20, 1.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 7, <hi>to</hi> 15. <hi>of</hi> 12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Numb.</hi> 1,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 14, 2. <hi>to the end.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 28, 10.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 
                        <hi>Amos</hi> 2, <hi>to</hi> 9. <hi>of the</hi> 3,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.10.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 8. <hi>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        </hi> 21. <hi>to end</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 37, 1.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 
                        <hi>Obad all</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Leuit</hi> 29.1.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 
                        <hi>Zach.</hi> 2, 14. <hi>to</hi> 8.3,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 32, 2.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> 
                        <hi>Mich.</hi> 3, 6, <hi>to</hi> 9, <hi>of</hi> 6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Numb.</hi> 8, 1. 22, 2.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:3176:59"/>
            <p>Theſe Bookes and Chapters of the olde and new Teſtament doo not agree by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon in all reſpects, but in ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars. And therefore I haue laid downe brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Argument of euerie Book in the new Teſtament, by the which you may the more eaſilie perceiue the like in the old, and make your compariſon fit.</p>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument of S. Mathew.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The incarnation of Chriſt. 1, 2.</item>
                  <item>2. The office of <hi>Iohn Baptist.</hi> 3.</item>
                  <item>3. The doctrine and miracles of Chriſt. 4, 5, 6, 8, 9, 11, 13, 14, 15, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21.</item>
                  <item>4. The names and offices of the twelue Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. 10.</item>
                  <item>5. The reproofe of ill life. 7, 12, 14, 16.</item>
                  <item>6. The holy Supper inſtituted. 26.</item>
                  <item>7. The Paſſeouer and reſurrection. 27, 28.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:3176:59"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>All 4. Euangelists agree in this, which is a ſtrong proofe of the truth and great dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of Gods Word, by the length of time, and distance of place in which it was written. One is more briefe than the other, and one handleth ſome thing larger than the other.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Mathew</hi> the humanitie of Chriſt, eight yeares after the aſcenſion of Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Marke</hi> is briefe in all: hee ſheweth the ende of the law, and deuideth the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, 10. yeares after Chriſts aſcenſion.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Luke</hi> the Office of Chriſt, by aboliſhing the workes of the lawe, fifteene yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Iohn</hi> the diuinitie of Chriſt, and the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God in ſpirit 32. yeres after Chriſt.</item>
               </list>
               <p>THe Author of the 14. Epiſtles was <hi>Paul,</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Beniamin,</hi> who was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable by birth, in reſpect whereof his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents named him after <hi>Saul</hi> the firſt King of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> He was called <hi>Paule</hi> in reſpect of his notable actions in conuerting <hi>Paulus Sergi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:3176:60"/> the great Conſull, as appeareth <hi>Act.</hi> 13. And for another cauſe vſed in change of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which I rather allow, to change their names, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was called <hi>Saphnat, Daniel Balthaſar, Ananias Sidrac, Azarias Abed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nago, Miſael Meſac.</hi> So <hi>Saule</hi> in the Lawe, <hi>Paule</hi> in the Goſpell. Hee was brought vp exquiſitely in the Law with <hi>Gamaliel, Act.</hi> 22. he liued verie orderlie after his conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. He wrote theſe Epiſtles in order as fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument to the Rom.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Romanes</hi> were <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing Chriſt in <hi>Rome,</hi> among whome were manie falſe teachers, which mooued S. <hi>Paule</hi> to write exhorting them to take heed thereof, and to increaſe in the knowledge of Chriſt, the dignitie of workes in the <hi>Iewes</hi> &amp; in the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> of ſinne, of faith, of grace, of iuſtification by faith, and in concluſion, of ſalutations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument of the <hi>1.</hi> Cor.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Corinthians</hi> had their originall of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthus,</hi> who built that citie, it was a place
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:3176:60"/> greatly frequented. In that Citie was the Temple dedicated to the Goddeſſe <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus.</hi> There was that great notorious whore <hi>Lais,</hi> ſpoken of ouer all the world; and there ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other whores: yet in this Citie God had his Church. Saint <hi>Paule</hi> continued there a yeare and 6. months preaching. But when he departed into <hi>Syria,</hi> manie falſe teachers en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in, and taught, that whoredome, ryor, drunkenneſſe, &amp;c. was lawfull, matrimonie vnlawfull; and they denied the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. S. <hi>Paule</hi> hearing of this, wrote this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to withdraw them from all theſe euills by particulars, with exhortations to remain in the doctrine he had taught them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>Argument of the 2. Cor.</head>
               <p>HEE excuſeth his long abſence by diuers troubles which hindred him, he willeth to excommunicate him that was taken in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultrie, &amp; he cleereth himſelfe of all blame towardes them, hee ſheweth difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the ſpirite and the letter, betweene the olde Teſtament and the new.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:3176:61"/>
               <head>Argument of the Gallat.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Gallathians</hi> were people of <hi>Aſia,</hi> after his departure thence, falſe teachers preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in, &amp; taught that the Ceremonies of the Lawe were to be kept, and they ſpake euil of this holy Apoſtle thereby to deface his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. Which mooued him to write vnto them, diſcharging himſelfe for the credit of his calling, &amp; confirming his doctrine, with the ouerthrow of their falſe opinions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>Argument of Epheſians.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>EPheſus</hi> was a famous Citie by the Sea of <hi>Ionius,</hi> where was a Temple dedicated to the falſe Goddeſſe <hi>Diana.</hi> S. <hi>Paule</hi> at his firſt comming ſtayed little there, but at the ſecond time he ſtayed 3. yeares: perceiuing that God had manie there to be ſaued euen among the Witches, Sorcerers, Inchaunters, &amp;c. Whereby the mercie of God appeared more abundantly. At his departure he left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them <hi>Elders,</hi> and <hi>Timothie</hi> as their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. This Argument agreeth nearely with the <hi>Romanes</hi> and <hi>Gallathians.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:3176:61"/>
               <head>The argument of the Philippians.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PHilip Macedon</hi> was the originall of that Citie: they had domeſticall troubles and diuers other loſſes for the Teſtimonie of Chriſt, wherefore he exhorteth them to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and watchfulneſſe,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The argument of the Colloſſ.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Colloſſians</hi> were a people of that great Citie <hi>Colloſſa.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was neuer with them. They were taught by <hi>Epaphras, One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus</hi> and <hi>Titichus.</hi> S. <hi>Paule</hi> heard that they were troubled with the <hi>Iewes</hi> about Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and with the <hi>Gentiles</hi> about wordes and ſubtill Philoſophie. Wherefore hee wrote vnto them to confirme them in that they had learned concerning Chriſt, and to confute the contrarie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument of 1. Theſſ.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THeſſalonica</hi> was a famous citie of <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia,</hi> whence the people had their name. He was among them but three <hi>Sabboths</hi> by reaſon of the <hi>Iewes.</hi> Hee ſent <hi>Timothie</hi> vnto
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:3176:62"/> them, by whom he vnderſtood of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie. Whereupon hee wrote vnto them, exhorting them to patience, to loue, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie, and to conſider well of the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument of 2. Theſs.</head>
               <p>HE excuſeth his long abſence, ſheweth the manner of the reſurrection, &amp; the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt: he dehorteth from curious queſtions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The argument of 1. Timothie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>TImothie</hi> his Father was a <hi>Graecian,</hi> his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a <hi>Iew,</hi> which was the cauſe that hee was not circumciſed in his infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie according the lawe. His mother <hi>Eunica</hi> and his grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother <hi>Loida</hi> were verie godlie, wherein they brought him vp. Saint <hi>Paule</hi> his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſent him in the Lords buſines to diuers places: in the ende he was left at <hi>Epheſus</hi> as their Biſhop: to whom he wrote this Epiſtle about the choyce of Paſtors in the Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:3176:62"/>
               <head>The Argument of <hi>2. Timothie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>TImothie</hi> did greatlie mourne after <hi>Paule:</hi> he therefore did write to comfort him, and withall to ſhewe him how he was hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in priſon, which was the cauſe that he came not to <hi>Epheſus</hi> according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument of <hi>Titus.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>TItus</hi> was a Graecian borne, Saint <hi>Paule</hi> was his maſter, who left him at <hi>Creete</hi> to conſtitute Miniſters in euerie Pariſh, and to reforme their manners. <hi>Titus</hi> was a young man, therefore his maſter wrote this Epiſtle that he ſhould doo nothing raſhlie. What kind of Paſtors were to bee allowed, and what not.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument of <hi>Philemon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PHilemon</hi> was of <hi>Colloſſentia,</hi> a rich man, a godlie man, and a liberall, he had a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant called <hi>Oneſimus,</hi> who departed from him and ſtole his money: when he heard S. <hi>Paule</hi> preach, he beleeued in Ieſus Chriſt,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:3176:63"/> and he confeſſed his fault. Wherevpon Saint <hi>Paule</hi> wrote to his maſter, exhorting him to forgiue his ſeruant.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument of the <hi>Haebrues.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are diuers opinions concerning the authoritie hereof. Some ſay it is not Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall: ſome ſay it is not <hi>Paules</hi> writing: ſome ſay it is Saint <hi>Paules</hi> Epiſtle, but not Canonicall, becauſe (ſay they) there is no mention of his name, and the ſtile is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. The trueth is by the beſt and moſt god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie learned, that it is Saint <hi>Paules</hi> writing and Canonicall, becauſe the matter is conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the reſt of his Epiſtles. The Graecians did ſo allow of it, and the ſame was confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Councell of <hi>Nicen. Nicephorus</hi> ſaith, that it was written in Haebrue by Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> and tranſlated into Greeke by Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> who altered the ſtile and method. <hi>Irae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus</hi> who was <hi>Policarpus</hi> ſcholler ſaide the ſame, the trueth thereof being receiued from Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> who was <hi>Policarpus</hi> maſter: ſuch was the obſtinacie of the <hi>Iewes</hi> reſiſting the doctrine of Chriſt. That gaue occaſion to Saint Paule to write, exhorting them from
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:3176:63"/> the hardnes of their hearts: he magnifieth Chriſt aboue the Prophets, <hi>Moſes, Aaron, Leui,</hi> and all other offices, who fulfilled the prophecies, accompliſhed the lawe, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered a more perfect ſacrifice than they all. Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh of certeine in the 6. Chapter, and 10. who had reuolted from the knowne trueth wittinglie, willinglie, ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornlie and preſumptuouſlie, that were not by the word of God to bee ſaued, therefore he altereth much of his ſtile and phraſe, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciallie at the beginning and ending.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument of <hi>Iames.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the 10. of <hi>Mathew</hi> mention is made of two <hi>Iames,</hi> the one was the ſonne of <hi>Zebe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deus,</hi> the other, the ſonne of <hi>Alpheus.</hi> It is certaine the Author of this Epiſtle was <hi>Iames</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Alpheus,</hi> who is in that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter called <hi>Lebbeus</hi> and <hi>Thaddeus.</hi> He is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the brother of <hi>Jude</hi> and the brother of our Lord, <hi>Gal. 1, 19.</hi> Hee was the ſonne of <hi>Mary Cleophas,</hi> who was ſiſter to the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary.</hi> It is the phraſe of Scripture to call <hi>Couſens, Bretheren.</hi> This Epiſtle is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Catholicall, becauſe it is to all people.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:3176:64"/> The ſumme thereof is to inſtruct all men how to liue, how to beleeue: He ſetteth out the conuerſation of thoſe that are regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, of faith, of patience, and of their tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument of 1. <hi>Peter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis <hi>Peter</hi> was by all conſent the author of this Epiſtle. He was called <hi>Simon</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Fiſher:</hi> Chriſt named him <hi>Cephas,</hi> which is <hi>Peter. Mark.</hi> 3. he was one of the Apoſtles and the chiefeſt for diuers cauſes. He ſpeaketh of workes after regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as Saint <hi>James</hi> doth: he deſcendeth into the dueties of each degree, and of the conuerſion of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> It was written vpon the occaſion that <hi>Siluanus</hi> being long with Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> and trauailing to <hi>Babilon</hi> met with Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> who deliuered him this Epiſtle generall, to <hi>Gentiles</hi> and <hi>Iewes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument of the 2. Epistle of <hi>Peter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE exhorteth all men from day to day, and from degree to degree, to encreaſe
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:3176:64"/> in the workes of regeneration, to beware of falſe teachers, the ſtate of the laſt times. He thought his death to bee at hand, wherefore he wrote to the glorie of his maſter Chriſt. <hi>2. Pet. 1.14, 15.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument of the 1. Epistle of <hi>Iohn.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis <hi>Iohn</hi> was one of the foure Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, he was the ſonne of <hi>Zebedeus,</hi> belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of Chriſt and wrote the Reuelation. He exhorteth to faith, to brotherlie loue, to trie and approoue the ſpirits, to auoide falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, hypocriſie, ſmall offences, and to deck themſelues with godlie liuing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument of the 2. Epistle of <hi>Iohn.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HErein he handleth mutuall loue, the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of widowes, to beware of falſe Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, a way to know them, and with whom is no fellowſhip laid downe. He wrote eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciallie to a certaine godlie widowe, who with her children and houſehold laboured after Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:3176:65"/>
               <head>The Argument of the 3. Epistle of <hi>Iohn.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN this Epiſtle he exhorteth his familiar friends and his hoſt <hi>Gains,</hi> &amp;c. thanking GOD for the great comfort receiued at his hands, he laid him downe as a harborer of all that loued Ieſus Chriſt. He exhorteth to conſtancie, and to beware of Tyrants.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument of <hi>Iude.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE was one of the Apoſtles, he inſtructeth the godlie to continue in well doing. He ſheweth the Iuſtice of God againſt ſinners and reuolters, as, the Angels, the Iewes, Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument of the <hi>Reuelation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis booke containeth all the doctrine of the Prophets concerning Chriſt, which was to be accompliſhed after his comming. The comfort that commeth by his death: how to know the falſe ſpirit, the battaile be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Church and the limmes of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:3176:65" rendition="simple:additions"/> the mariage of Chriſt with his Saints, the prouidence of God, and the force of his word.</p>
               <p>Now, the verie GOD of peace ſanctifie you throughout: and I pray God that your whole ſpirit, ſoule and bodie, may bee kept blameles vnto the comming of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. Faithfull is he which calleth you, which will alſo doo it. <hi>1. Theſſ. 5.23, 24.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3176:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3176:66"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
